<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theauraujohn his Theous ori apokolipikal: or, Gods light declared in mysteries Salem ori ad te Israel. Theauraujohn Tanni. Dedicated to the army and the risen people in all lands, coming forth in the first fruits in the evangelical operation. To these is the dedication of this book; and their eyes behold the truth, none else. I have added to this book the particular charges in the indictment against Captain Robert Norwood and my self, and my defence against the charge.</title>
            <author>Tany, Thomas, fl. 1649-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E640_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206664</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170906</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94576)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170906)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2520:18b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theauraujohn his Theous ori apokolipikal: or, Gods light declared in mysteries Salem ori ad te Israel. Theauraujohn Tanni. Dedicated to the army and the risen people in all lands, coming forth in the first fruits in the evangelical operation. To these is the dedication of this book; and their eyes behold the truth, none else. I have added to this book the particular charges in the indictment against Captain Robert Norwood and my self, and my defence against the charge.</title>
                  <author>Tany, Thomas, fl. 1649-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and are to be sold by Giles Calvert at the Black-Spread-Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Tany.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug 13".</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 2520:18b, bound and filmed with Wing T152A, Wing T152D, and Wing T156.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion and politics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170906:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>JOHN</hi> His THEOUS ORI APOKOLIPIKAL: Or, Gods Light declared in Myſteries. <hi>Salem Ori ad te Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Beware of falſe Prophets, that come to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly are raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wolves.</p>
               <p>But behold, Chriſt hath told you, By their fruit you ſhall know them.</p>
               <p>Beloved, God is love, and love is light, and in it is no darkneſs at all.</p>
               <p>So then know, he that is in light, acts in love, not luſt; and he that acts not in love, is in darkneſs even till now.</p>
               <p>I will pour out my Spirit in the laſt days, and that Spirit ſhall be your alone teacher, ſaith the Lord my God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jehovah Ire ad te, O England.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Theauraujohn Tanni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dedicated to the Army and the riſen people in all Lands, coming forth in the firſt fruits in the Evangelical operation.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. <hi>14.1.</hi>
               </bibl> And ſo a lamb ſtood on Mount Sion, and with him an hundred forty and four thouſand, having his Fathers name written in their foreheads. <hi>To theſe is the dedication of this Book; and their eyes behold the Truth, none elſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>I have added to this Book the particular Charges in the Indictment againſt Captain <hi>Robert Norwood</hi> and myſelf, and my Defence againſt the Charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170906:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170906:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He word grafted in our ſouls, makes oneneſs in unione in our lives and converſation, for God teaches us to be like himſelf in love. Dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, I am conſtrained to publiſh to the view of the world the writing I have declared. It is to a tittle without alteration, as every Epiſtle ſtands in his place without adding or diminiſhing one tittle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my oath I will affirm, though ſometime I was out of my ſelf, yet the Charge of calumny upon me being ſo great. I am forced to declare my greateſt weakneſs, which might have been in obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But I beſeech the courteous Reader, know that the great ſound and name of things are not the very things themſelves; for if ſo Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſuffered juſtly all whereas charged upon them, but Chriſt and his Apoſtles were one truth and the dark world perſecuted them even unto death; now know that the new heaven and the new earth is not yet erected in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and till that work of Grace and power come, there is, and muſt be enmity betwixt light and darkneſs: condemn not things by another mans ſight, but know, that thou whoſoever thou art, muſt be ſaved in thy own ſight and light, and not in another mans. Every man muſt give an account of himſelf but bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren I am accounted a blaſphemer, now I am come to try the truth in your Goſpel, the Goſpel in me that you account blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, hath made me act ſtrangely; and whether truly or no, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:170906:3"/>to the truth in the ſame Goſpel, I commit to judgement. Now if you condemn me for blaſphemy, and my actions are the very ſubſtance that Goſpel or writing points at or unto; I ſay that then my blaſphemy is holineſs, and you are found blaſphemers with your high cry of holineſs. Now brethren I muſt have you come from your high cry of names, and by things you are and muſt be juſtified, and I will put in my actions in the balance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am but one, and many againſt me. Firſt know, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fourteen weeks in humiliation, in faſting and Prayer frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Then the power fell upon me in my ſhop, and ſmote me dumb, then after blinde, and then dead, in the beholding of hundreds of people; then I was corded and bound in my bed, and then I received inſtruction, which afterwards I was forced to put the ſame into action: which was this Diſtribute all to the poor Releaſe all pawns, without advantage, give back to them that were not able to redeem; fain to proclaim if I had injured or wronged any man to reſtore him four-fold, according to the Law. Brethren, the name of this would not ſerve me, for I was forced to act the thing, I durſt not act any thing. O beloved, the Goſpel is peace in it ſelf, but 'tis a fiery Law to fleſh and blood. Now how have I walked ſince my affliction? can any man charge me either for drinking, ſwearing, whoring or deceiving, or lying, or uncivil walking? which do you know, and all the world, that blaſphemy is the root on which them names depend; and where a godly life is, there theſe actions are not to be found; and where godlineſs is not in the root or ſoul, theſe are and will be: for know, that blaſphemy is onely the tye in the ſoul of man, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from its principle of obedience, and from that looſneſs, comes a diſſoluteneſs in life; and take Chriſts own word, which is this, By their fruits, that is actions, you ſhall know them. Again, what end or advantage have I ſought to my ſelf, ever ſince, as my Epiſtles will declare? now I ſay, the love of Chriſt hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained me hereunto, which is not blaſpemy; but love in truth, without deceit. Now brethren, you that are ſo high in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in name, I come to ſee what things you declare, for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is not a lying name, but an over-powring and commanding
<pb facs="tcp:170906:3"/>thing; who amongſt you is gone beyond this blaſphemy I have ſtated, and who is but ſhort of what I have ſpoken and done he is a blaſphemer and a perjured man, for 'tis written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain:</hi> and have ye not all learned and heard that it is not ſpeaking, but doing, is the juſtification of him that doth it, and a declaration to the world, that God hath done his work in him from whence this doing doth proceed? So then, be ye hearers no more, deceiving your own ſelves, but doers. O how many high expreſſions of Chriſt, and holineſs and the Lord help you, before five pound to help to relieve him in need; nay, five ſhillings; now if you ſay that the Goſpel is true, I ſay 'tis made a lye by you, for that being truth, commands thee not to ſpeak without acting, and thou ſpeakſt all and acts not, which action is the life of the Goſpel; and in truth, and indeed, how many of you are without the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel for your cloak? <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Pure religion and undefiled, before God, even the Father, is this, To viſit the fatherleſs and widows in their adverſity, and to keep himſelf unſpotted of the world.</hi> Brethren this is a metaphorical expreſſion, but I will give you the literal meaning, that is this: the fatherleſs hold in it all that are in need; for as the Father is the ſtaffe on which the whole Creation depends, ſo the fatherleſs amongſt us is all that are in want, ſo as God in his mercy and love condeſcends to our relief: ſo to condeſcend to the fatherleſs, is no leſs then helping all in need; &amp; the widow is but the ſame, for to give out to the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of our knowing our duty that we may be left without excuſe, for we that make a God of the letter, for if we dwel in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, in the knowledge of the letter, that letter ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us, and Gods judgement ſhall finde us; for wo unto him that doth acknowledge the letter to be true, and he not reformed in outward obedience to the ſame,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to ſerve you in unfained Love.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Theauraujohn</item>
                     <item>Tanniour</item>
                     <item>Allah al</item>
                     <item>Sabbah Skribahjail.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170906:4"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 16. adde <hi>her.</hi> p. 7. l. 6. for <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ited</hi> r. <hi>deitied.</hi> p. 11. l. 6. after, <hi>we could be,</hi> r. <hi>A Sambah, or your Sam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrength in God.</hi> p. 13. l. 12. for <hi>here,</hi> r. <hi>there.</hi> Ibid. l 36. for <hi>Arminia,</hi> r. <hi>Armen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi> p. 15. l. 10. for <hi>ſapait,</hi> r. <hi>ſapuit.</hi> p. 17. l. 29 &amp; 30. for <hi>Noon,</hi> r. <hi>Moon.</hi> p. 18. l. 15. r. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny thing leſs.</hi> p. 22. l. penult. for <hi>rea,</hi> r. <hi>arc.</hi> p. 26. l. 30. for <hi>baſiſt,</hi> r. <hi>baſis.</hi> p. 27. l. 27. for <hi>netet,</hi> r. <hi>nedet.</hi> Ibid. l. 36. for <hi>eſſence,</hi> 1. <hi>offence.</hi> Ibid. l. 4. for <hi>addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> r <hi>ſad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne.</hi> p. 28. l. 34. for <hi>aone,</hi> r. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove.</hi> p. 29. l. 14. for <hi>in,</hi> r. <hi>in o</hi> p. 31. l. 1. for <hi>ſobao,</hi> r. <hi>ſobaos.</hi> p. 34. l. 3. adde <hi>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> ibid. l. 33. for <hi>would,</hi> r. <hi>will.</hi> ibid. for <hi>doing,</hi> r. <hi>dung.</hi> p. 39. l. 23. dele <hi>that</hi> ibid. l. 26. for <hi>gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> r. <hi>grav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> ibid. l. 32. for <hi>cackt,</hi> r. <hi>act.</hi> p. 40. l. 3. for <hi>they,</hi> r. <hi>thy.</hi> ibid. l. 33. for <hi>Olimet,</hi> r. <hi>Clim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> p. 42. l. 16. adde <hi>a.</hi> ibid. l. 37. for <hi>God,</hi> r. <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> p. 43. l. 19. adde <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 44. l. 26. for <hi>illſtration,</hi> r. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lluſtration.</hi> p. 45. l. 9. adde <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u an.</hi> p. 46. l. 34. r. <hi>all the.</hi> ibid. l. ult. for <hi>tying,</hi> r. <hi>lying.</hi> p. 47. l. 4. r. <hi>to come.</hi> p. 51. l. 34. r. <hi>that are you lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h to own.</hi> p. 55. l. 28. dele <hi>God.</hi> p. 56. l. 22. for <hi>time,</hi> r. <hi>Trin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 57. l. 18. adde <hi>the.</hi> p. 59. l. 8. for <hi>cauſe,</hi> r. <hi>cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> p. 60. l. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or <hi>the,</hi> r. <hi>th y.</hi> p 62. l. 17. for <hi>from,</hi> r. <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 63. l. 25. for <hi>reader,</hi> r. <hi>leader.</hi> bid. l. penult. for <hi>in.</hi> r. <hi>its.</hi> p. 64. l. 37. dele <hi>of.</hi> ibid. l. 40. for <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound,</hi> r. <hi>bound.</hi> p. 67. l. 15. for <hi>humany,</hi> r. <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</hi> p. 68. l. 5. for <hi>deely,</hi> r. <hi>deeply.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170906:4"/>
            <head>Dr. <hi>Ba. Jhones</hi> his Letter of Queries to <hi>Theaurau John Tanniour.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have often wondred that men ſhould ſo jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle about the circumſtance of Religion, whiles the end of the thing it ſelf (if we may proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo call a <hi>non entity</hi>) remains ſo obſcure. The end of Religion I take to be the well being of man after death. To which is neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired an ability to compare qualities, and then (at leaſtwiſe opinionately) to judge of them: Which, how it is retained in and after death, the more I ſearch for in the Books of the Learned, the more I confeſs I remain diſſatisfied. So that I know not whether more properly to addreſs my ſelf for this point of knowledge, then to you. The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted mad-man of the times, who can ſpeak ſomwaht experimentally thereof; as having had at leaſt one foot in the Boat already, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore better prepared for Revelations of this kinde, then any other I know. Give me leave therefore to ask you:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Soul be a created ſubſtance, diſtinct from the Body; and conſequently departeth from the Body, in the moment of death; A perfect Creature, underſtanding not onely whence it came, but alſo knowing Acts, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> If ſo, to what end is the reſurrection of the Body? Or what need the Soul be reunited to it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if you finde that the Soul is traduced with the Body, Then when is its ſeparation? Whether (though this be a Queſtion unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Phyloſopher to ask) in the moment of death? or upon the putrefaction of the Body? (which ſeems to be ſomwhat proved by the aparition of ſome mens ſhapes; ſome moneths after their deceaſe?) otherwiſe I ſhould propound to you this third Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether the whole man doth not reſt in the grave until the laſt Trump?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170906:5"/> 4. And laſtly, In what part or principle of the Creature doth this Germen of knowledge reſide?</p>
            <p n="5">5. And after the diſſolution of the compound, by what Organs actuated?</p>
            <p>To enlarge my ſelf to you on theſe were impertinent, ſince you reſolv'd me that at other times you cannot reaſon thoſe diſcoveries that are revealed to you in your tranſportations.</p>
            <p>For the Practical Part of Theology, enough to me is, That one Precept of (let not the Authors name affright you) <hi>Mahomet</hi> in his <hi>Alkaron,</hi> viz. To reſign my ſelt unto my God, and be an honeſt man. However, if you could reconcile that fatal neceſſity of the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> with the free-will of <hi>Arminius,</hi> I conceive you would thereby put an end to moſt of the controverſies now on foot amongſt the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Lodging by <hi>Jame</hi>'s fields <date>this 7 March. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours affectionately</hi> Ba. Jhones.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Anſwer to this Letter followeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170906:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Theaurau John</hi> his Salvat-ori, or the true knowledge in light.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have here inſerted the ſtate, and the diſcovery made to me:</p>
            <p>Firſt, as for the ſoul, it is no created ſubſtance, for 'tis the divine breath of God, or it may properly be ſaid (if radically underſtood) the life of God, in the humane body; not of the body, but incloſed within the circumference of the body, That is to ſay, the living life of our Spirit, yet intire in it ſelf, free, abſolute, unneceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, acting truth; this is the Image of God in Man: Now at the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the life returns to the fountain from whence it had its Origine: The groſs material body Beſtial, returns into the influences; for know, the influences from the ſtars, draws with the Sun the Foy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter under the Earth, through the earth into the receptacle of the Moon, for the Moon is a receptacle, of the updraft from the earth, as well as ſhe is a receptacle of the celeſtial influences, into her Conclave, to let down his congealment, into the Terreſtrial Orbs. This is touching the corporal, or earthly body; now the ſpiritual body in Man, is of a divine nature; for there is a natural body and a ſpiritual body.</p>
            <p>The Divine or Evangelical body is Spiritual; That cannot be viewed with humane eyes, which hath a reſtoration, after the putting of this earthly body: That body is life, underſtanding, and a reſtoied body by Chriſt, that is the life of God; that is the Paradaical body: Now this body is not capable of any ſorrow nor joy, for tis perfect, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection admits of no more; for if more, or leſs, not perfection; but 'tis Joy it ſelf: Now this is Chriſts body of his Saints; the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is at the parting the bodies at death; To ſay the Soul re-enters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the body, 'tis madneſs; for know that this body is but the caſe, and the wiſdom remains within the inmoſt body that is ſpiritual, and departs with that: The body earthly is clay and dung. Now to the ſhort definition. The Soul, or Spirit, Is, the life of God in our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, abſolutely free, unneceſſitated, which at its ſeparation return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to its center.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170906:6"/>
            <p> The groſs body earthly into the Influences: The ſpiritual body into the Evangelical living, with it all wiſdom and knowledge in the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: So there is the Death, Reſurrection, and Reſtoration, the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Execution, and condemnation: For the humane taſts death, that the Spirit may take life; for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We groan and are burthened, and would be unclothed, that mortality might be ſwallowed up of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſack ally Oly Sabbat allu ſah.</hi> The light returneth, and departeth to the everlaſting God. <hi>An ſi ſabie corpus ſolat or arryre</hi> xx. And the body remains with the Mettals to be refined. <hi>Cax-alli ſabdi one apolo mo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abfi.</hi> The remainder of its adherents returns into Generations. <hi>Callu Evangelious inſem ſabat al.</hi> The Evangelical body is buryed in the high thing, that is God, or Chriſt, Jah, or Jehovah: So that here you ſee, the body ſaved, the body deſtroyed; the ſoul centered: <hi>Tu eſt vita ammi mem:</hi> The life of my people is perfection in me: <hi>O O ſolo ogagous in ſuolo ſabdi ſapuit:</hi> O the high wonder in man, is the Light of God. <hi>Glory to him alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the practical part of <hi>Theos-logi:</hi> But to render it in your own term, 'Tis improper: For the Negation doth tie up the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the word in its proper eſſential center is Theos-ologi, that is to ſay, Gods Light in the excellency of his declaratives, or as you will have it, his declaratives of his excellency; ſo much for Theologi, or in propriety of ſpeech Theos-ologi. Now Theos-ologi is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Samba,</hi> or and your Theology is derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Hebrew Radaxes is <hi>Thauſi alli;</hi> that is thus much: The high declaratives of truth from thoſe Characters <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Non tu reſignatus, non ſè, ſed oli operat ad te oli;</hi> thou reſigneſt not thy ſelf, but light taketh thee into it ſelf: As for <hi>Mahomet,</hi> he is blindneſs or darkneſs, his name denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates no leſs, for 'tis derived from <hi>Mazzum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the declared truth by man: know, it cannot reconcile the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt men; For if it could, then man could confer Gods gift; but though God do cauſe in man the declarative of truth, that hath his Seal upon it, yet men do not always aſſent to it, by reaſon of the darkneſs in themſelves.</p>
            <p>But for the fatal neceſſity of the Stoicks, 'tis a grammered learned learning, that will not be unbottomed eaſily, though clearly confuted, that in this ſhort abſtract, I leave to the Judgement of all.</p>
            <p>For the neceſſity of Salvation, 'Tis not to be obtained by Man, neither is it loſt by Man: Thus, that that man can attain, 'tis not God; for then the attainer, is as great as the attained, or greater; undenyable by any, for the maxime will hold, and will not admit of any Negation in the coertive part, for in that ſtate there cannot be two equals, as to ſay two Gods, and never a Creation; but you muſt hold God, and the Created by God.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170906:6"/>
            <p> So much for attaining Salvation. Now man cannot loſe his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus: That that can be loſt, that can have no center; and take your own words, the Soul lives ever, and all times is a center in one time; that is, in God. Now know that the Soul as you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> count it, is eſſenced in God, and if the Soul could deliuate or detract its Eſſence, then it is a greater God then he that gave it a being in himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now for Free-will that the <hi>Arminians</hi> hold, 'Tis blindneſs in their ſeeming center: For Free-will is free obedience of will, to him that gave it a beeing, of his own free will in Light; which Freewill is Chriſts free obedience, which is Gods free mercy; which is called Chriſt the Saviour: But to ſpeak home, the number of names of things are all but the Hyroglificy of one thing, in which that one delighteth; in the goodneſs of the beholding his things made: One more, Heaven, Earth all things, are but a caſe for the Divinity to operate or act forth in.</p>
            <p>Leſt you ſhould object and ſay, That Free-will is not fully confuted, Take this: The Free-will in man, is but his free conceit, of his Free-will; in which Will he is looſed from the tye of his center: Thus, his will is Free, in that his will is freed by Chriſts freedom; but then 'tis not his will, but 'tis a Divine Will; freed by the Free-will of Chriſts obedience. <hi>Satis eſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170906:7"/>
            <head>Epiſtle I.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved by divine inſpiration, I being lighted in the Evangelical and Sacred Myſtery, and Hiſtory, which is divine in it ſelf, and by polluted man, the divine and evangelical light in its ſpecies is ſo far vilified, that the luſture is buried in the grave of mans car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality: O the Tranſcendent Excellency in the divine being, that it that is all, and all things, ſhould be ſo far by mans wiſdom tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to another thing, that is <hi>Adam</hi> in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: His work now to unwork this <hi>Adam,</hi> and unbury this buried truth; 'tis God his work, in the reſtoring him, and giving him his that was at firſt, a perfect name that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Hamah: Now this name, named on, and in by God, on and upon his new Creature, 'tis life and ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; for he that gives that name confers himſelf into that new thing named by himſelf. Now beloved I being named by God, that name being <hi>Reuben Theaurou John,</hi> the extent of the ſignification, is the firſt ſtrength in the evangelical and divine light, in the tranſcendency of its own excellency, that is into God himſelf: Beloved this new name, named by God; the effects flowing from that ingrafted ſtem, 'tis love, and for your ſakes my brethren, for God is union, yet diſtillative into three perſons, but from and into unions Deity, ſo to be named by God, the name cauſes the named to be turned into a diſtillative, that this name hath received, the effects that flow, is love, elſe not new named: Beloved to be named by God, 'tis to be reſtored by Chriſt, this glory ſhakes your rotten foundations, that, that is may remain unſhaken.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170906:7"/>
            <p> Now <hi>Adam</hi> in darkneſs is the Law in its demonſtrative, but <hi>Hamah</hi> in Chriſt is reſtoratived in and unto from whence he was faln: Now beloved comes the true ſtate of <hi>Adam,</hi> as you reade it: The thing in your intendant is truth, but ſpelled by a ſalfe name: Now <hi>Hamah</hi> was the firſt Light that gave a being to its adherent; for it was the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Deity, deited in and unto it ſelf, <hi>in ſe, &amp; in ſe, &amp; in ſc,</hi> infol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, infolding, infolding in it ſelf; unfolding is created by, and from the infoldings of himſelf, he unfolded and we came forth, not into a garden, but upon the ſpecies of the earth: Be not ignorant, could a Garden compaſs and confine his creative? No, no, the creations of numerous men and women at once, and your <hi>Adam</hi> is not man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man but the whole creation of God, which is his declaratives of his Excellency, in and from him that cannot be limitted for millions of millions, Nay all that were that is, and is to come, is but one to him, which is your <hi>Adam</hi> and my <hi>Hamah:</hi> But the difference is, your inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <hi>Adam</hi> was light and became dark; My <hi>Hamah</hi> is and was light: Look to it, for both light and darkneſs in one name, <hi>Hamah</hi> not in your <hi>Adam;</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> is death, becauſe a lye, and <hi>Hamah</hi> is light, and was and to come the ſame: <hi>Hamah</hi> is Jeſus, Jehovah, Eloal, L. The all of all, and in all things: Now in this ſtate all God, no man: In <hi>Adam</hi> all man, no God; but by God yea are: Beloved I beſeech you minde, for it is not mans words, but the eternal Spirit renued in me dictating it ſelf into your underſtanding, to cauſe you forth to ariſe out of your deſpicable deſtroy'd eſtate, to make an inlet into that Holy of Holies, Chriſt the hope of Glory in me, in you both into one, to bring the eternal unchangeable Decree to its Center and extended Period, which is himſelf: Now to open <hi>Hamah</hi> truely it is to ſhew you the boſom of the Father, which no <hi>Adam</hi> can do, becauſe he is in a loſt condition, but <hi>Hamah</hi> can open himſelf: Minde this ſtate, it is the greateſt Myſtery that ever was opened; Nay it is the ſealed Book that none was able to open, that cauſed <hi>John</hi> to weep: Now is come the judgement of the Great Day that ſhall burn as an oven, and all the proude ſhall be ſtuble for that Flame.</p>
            <p>And I looked and behold no man was worthy to open the Seals: what are the ſeven Seals? they are perfection pointed unto: That ſtate is alluſive to the glorious tranſcendency in the eternal reſt; that them ſeven Seals pointed unto, for <hi>John</hi> knew that God would mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the opening of them ſeven Seals, at the appearance of Jeſus in his tranſcendant effate, which all have pointed unto that hath been prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that is, that the Glory of Glories ſhould be manifeſted to the ſons of men: Now I beſeech you minde, God is one and in himſelf, yet varieties in and from that one; God created all things: (That ſtate is undeniable) by Jeſus Chriſt, he made the world: Now what Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is, will be made known, that ſay you was <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſon the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170906:8"/>Carpenter, and the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> (thank the Popiſh tranſlation for that if it be worth it) but the truth in the eternal being, is, That Jeſus Chriſt is the boſom of, nay in the Father, yet farther it is the wiſdom of God, nay it is himſelf: And he could not be properly be ſaid to be born of One, that was the Birth of all; but one is God, and from that God all came forth: Now Jeſus Chriſt I acknowledge; but to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive in the womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> I deny, the intendant of your ſtory (as is ſited) I muſt deny? thus that that holy thing, and the Virgin ſtated, is an alluſive ſtate tranſcendant, the compoſing in one that is all: yet let me tell you, that the Virgin that ſhall conceive and bring forth her firſt birth, it is another thing intendant in the explacatory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flue, for it is the birth of God in and forth from our ſpirits: The Vir gin is the womb of our ſouls, not ſouls but ſpirits, not ſpirits but the ſpirit of the ſpirits in the conclave, aſſome, or bottom, in the which is inherent the Deity; this is ſomewhat to the matter: Now the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin is Jeſus: Chriſt the ſon is the Virgin, the work the ſame: This is the true Trinity, figurative in the earthly man, that is the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Deity: God dwelleth in us by his Spirit: Now this Spirit is Chriſt in us the hope, nay it is the Fathers glory: I acknowledge a man named Jeſus Chriſt, that he was the evangelical Life of God, as Paul was the evangelical Life of God, and the reſt were ſo; but he was the firſt in the firſt Trine, and the ſpirit dwelt in him in its flue, that is in its fulneſs, that I acknowledge glory due to, is to the perfect Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that is Light, that is in its union, God himſelf, and in his decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Chriſt with us, that is his Spirit in us, which is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you Brethren be careful, that you graſpe not to your ſelves a God and Saviour that God never ſent you, that is the body of Chriſt ſo named; take heed that you adore not that, that is not, and let ſlip that that is: For I tell you the fleſh of Chriſts fleſhly body pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth you no more then your own fleſh, nor the words that are named of him unto you; but it is this that is your ſalvation, that Spirit that was in that Body, that is, he that is not toucht with humanity, and yet dwells in fleſh, and not fleſh, but Spirit; that is, the divine Deity, which is the mercy it ſelf ſaving you, by cauſing a reſurrection of it ſelf to ariſe in you, and by that you are renued from Death to Life, that is, Chriſt the Son of the eternal God: Now the body of Jeſus cannot be defined, for it carries in it the inclue of every thing, for it is all things, and in all things, and by it all things are continued: The body of Man, is not this beaſtial body; for the true eſſential body of Man, is Chriſt. Now to the Body Bodily of and in Man; Be amaſed at the deſcription: The body of Man as you term it, is a Perſon, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I grant, yet no Perſon but three perſons; for it is the created of the three Unions Deity, and the Life of all them Three live in Man, and not Man, and by it man is, and was, and ſhall be: Now how could
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170906:8"/>Man fall, having three perſons in himſelf: Thus he fell, how? Not by eating an Apple, but by being nothing, That is, he is nothing, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be nothing, Thus, he was not at firſt: I was, not he; he is by me: O Lord how wonderful is thy marveilous hidden depths. I made man in my own Image: he defaced it, how could he; by being more then I would impart: That is the Tree, if ſo accounted be.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 30. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>The aurauſohn Tainniour Sabbah Skribahſail.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>BEloved, This day is fulfilled that holy Prophecy that ſaith, <hi>I will gather into one fold, Jew and Gentile, and David my ſervant ſhall be their king.</hi> That is Herogliphically, alluſive, or pointing to another: Now my Brethren, both ſews, and Gentiles; I am a ſew, begotten by the Goſpel, Circumciſed both in fleſh and ſpirit: By the life of Jeſus reſtored from <hi>Adam</hi> (as you call him) into <hi>Hamah,</hi> that extent is into God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; a Prieſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi> after <hi>Aaron,</hi> after Jeſus, after <hi>Paul,</hi> after <hi>Luke,</hi> after <hi>John,</hi> whoſe ſubſtance I am: I beſeech you minde, here is the Divinity declared in the Humanity, and yet not humanity, nor touched with humanity; The depth of the myſtery the ſpirit is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerner, and not fleſh. Now beloved, the Jews were loſt when the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was preached: The Gentiles loſt in their Jeſus, and Jeſus another thing then the Gentiles worſhip: ſo both loſt, that in one both may be found.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>January</hi> 20. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170906:9"/>
            <head>Epiſt. II.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Divinity of Chriſt is the beloved of God the Father, the Son in us; we in the Father: This is the reſtored <hi>Hamah,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> Beloved, having been drawn into the boſom of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the eternal ſpirit, in the which Spirit I dictate forth unto you the hidden depths of the eternal wiſdom, and foreknowledge of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> though declared in the appointed time, in himſelf, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in variety <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into unity <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is into himſelf, and in him both Jew and Gentile is one; and ſhall be one in themſelves, that is in Love <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and that root is God himſelf; for we are his off-ſpring. The divine Law is a coming to take its regency in the ſpecies of this world, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength ſhall come in the wiſdom, power, and excellency of it; yea the earth ſhall be enlightened with the luſtre and tranſcendency of that divine light <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Now to ſtate the ſtate that we are loſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſin is the cauſe now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> O <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> O <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> O <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> O <hi>orarau in ſalem abſi ſiſſere,</hi> O the morning light, that doth bring us again from our buried condition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is the Star in <hi>Jacob</hi> our Father, O the tranſcendency of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wiſdom. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> O the excellency in truth, the declaratives thereof ſhall be illuſtrated to the confounding ſelf-righteouſneſs, and inherent pride ſhall become abortive in the ſpecies of this world, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſin ſhall be diſcovered, her foundation raced, her rubbiſh caſt into the abyſs, and on her foundation ſhall righteouſneſs raign: for <hi>where</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſin doth abound, grace ſhall much more abound;</hi> O wonderful the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the great-deep is, and ſhall be opened unto the view of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Creation: Beloved, What is <hi>Hamah</hi> or <hi>Adam?</hi> To let you know, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah</hi> is God, 'tis Man, 'tis Earth, 'tis Ayr, 'tis Fire, 'tis Water; 'tis all, and the all of al things: This is <hi>Hamah</hi> in his firſt principle, or your intendant <hi>Adam:</hi> Minde the Myſtery, <hi>Hamah</hi> or <hi>Adam</hi> in God all things, in him even in <hi>Adam</hi> or <hi>Hamah:</hi> Look you curious generation that are Eagle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe ſouls are caſt off with the quickneſs of your underſtanding: the truth in the heart in the ſame man, that formed innocent Babe in the center is a lye in the evaporation and utterance: O the Head, the head, the head ſpoyls many a declarative truth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Now truth is the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, the <hi>Vita,</hi> the <hi>Evangelicales in rem,</hi> the Evangelical living in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170906:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>that thing intendant in this ſtate is ſchovah, that Jehovah our Throne, where we ſhall raign in union; Man is God, God is Man; this is the garden that is fained Paradiſe, but the true intendant is <hi>Adam,</hi> or <hi>Hamah</hi> in his firſt principle, that is he in the eternal Spirit, it in him, both in one; both unclothed, clothed is the fall that is being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when we could not be ſaid to be; we no looner were, but we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell by weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: What ignorance ſo ſtupid, that doth not perceive, that within himſelf is a ſtraining to the Center: That is, the weak Babe would go to the Mother to be clothed upon; that word of <hi>Pauls</hi> is dubious, 'tis better ſaid to be taken into, which is the proper Orthodox word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ori abſait ſedet me:</hi> O, when ſhall I ſit in the divine Light! <hi>Arrat a ſapit ad me mecam,</hi> the divine light taketh us into himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>abdi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat oli oſo ari</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſcle teuei mem nebet ammi niſan addi oon olo hiſſait arri ſoan abni allati, neſat ole abbi denat abſi orat hoſaret alua tueat adni beneat, oli ſana, abſi meltah:</hi> The derivacie. <hi>Hem oen ſanu eal abſe hocat all a cuti oau ſene een ſele lona mam ſebat abbi hoſaret ſeui neat adma hoſana alleu ene oi pele terte euan aſabdi huſuoli inſe meat adni tele peen peu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tai tran in lagoas a ſalla hori pean tebe hele phecatt adni avit ille next averrit hui medet alvat abſi tele nene ori appa ſabb oſoli dele mene nan ſagat abſi teucoeſalvah eni ori abſaet steutolen in ſe abat anni tere eſet ackri in le menet hoſaten oli pead adma amanet addeſh ſhela ariei ſele terte ſebat adma <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uan aſadi dene avat olo hoſaret a malta uanni tebe onat anni men ſola oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ret alvah</hi> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Engliſh derivacie.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now if you the Paradiſe would ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the heighth felicitie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the paradaical throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In which is onely unione.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the glory Celeſtial,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the life Evangelical,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the pavement of our God,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the Lilly, 'tis</hi> Aarons <hi>Rod;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the ſparkling glory in that skie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis inhabited withal all unitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the</hi> Aurorau, <hi>'tis the morn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the inclue our birth our born.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the union in three.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the Tran his excellencie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the light Celeſtial.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To be inhabited veſtual.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170906:10"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the glorious glory Throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That is the perfection in unione,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the Rod that rules the skie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the influe, nay Eternitie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the holy holy, holy one</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the Deity in</hi> una <hi>unione</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the three that Celeſtial bee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis the onely, onely, onely one;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That never was but is in one</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſtill the ſame remains in three</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here is unfolded a glimpſe of Paradicitee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here is a glimpſe of glory from that skie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That is that was, and ſhall be Eternitie.</hi> Allah ſabat.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> This we were: Now from this our fall begins <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now all you unvailed may plainly ſee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Fruit typ'd out by the forbidden Tree.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Know the fall is being created, for when we were not created, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come forth, we were as he is; that is in perfection: But coming forth from, we fell into theſe earthly forms as Senſitables, and Vegitables, yet again we were in innocency, then being ſo, but the Spirit of the great world took us into it, and ſo we became one with that; and two in our ſelves, that were unions in our ſelves, before we were his thirteen Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaſes, unions in themſelves; yet in Multiplicities in the Influences in their underſtanding: Now to finde this weakneſs out, and to diſcover it to the open view of blinde men I cannot, for it will trouble ſeeing men, to ſee into it; for the not ſeeing is the not knowing, and in that ſtate man is a beaſt and no more; now we were, and preſently we were not; this ſtate is myſterious, for that may truly be ſaid to be a myſtery that is not, nor cannot be known. Remember <hi>Johns</hi> ſealed book, and that is not opened to this very day: Now to the unfolding that Myſtery, that hath been hid from the view of the ſons of men, 'tis Paradice, what that is, what jeſus is, what <hi>Mary</hi> is, what hell is, that <hi>Abaddon</hi> that deceiver <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> what Paradice is from mans firſt principle, that is Jehovah: He and the Creation iſſued forth from the womb of the Deity, nay the Deity iſſued forth from itſelf into itſelf; deſentive, that is theſecond declarative, which is the Son, the ſecond perſon in the Trinity operative, for he ſaid, <hi>Let there be light,</hi> and behold the Sun, the life in all things, this is Jeſus, this is our Maſſah which is called the ſecond perſon in the Trinity deſentive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative, yet this is not the Son, 'tis the Father, 'tis not the Father nor the Son; 'tis one, and that union from whence all things do proceed, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170906:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>is the third perſon, for 'tis the product of both the other, neither one nor other, but either of, and in each other; and neither each other, but all three one; and they in union: This is Trinity in Unity, <hi>in ſe,</hi> in himſalf; but the great myſtery is how theſe three, yet one, dwels in the Creation, and not the Creation, nor in the Creation; yet in him, and by them all things do ſubſiſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in irineis ſem fratris: Mary</hi> is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from theſe Radaxes, ſhe is wrote <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> well knew the Papal ſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the perfection in the name, would cenceal the thing; But time will not admit truth to be declared in the luſturous excellency: What hell is, hell is ſtated for the wages due to this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſin</hi> charactar: Now to diſcover what them two are, them two are three; nay, them are one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſin;</hi> Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is no character in the whole Alphabet that carries the peats as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth, but ſtands as it were rooted in the earth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sambah</hi> ſhe ſtands like <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> on her ſoul <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>phe</hi> carries an half ſole <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>caph</hi> a quarter ſole, now theſe four Characters <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> carries her three points open upward, and her demonſtratives is to open upward, for the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upward, and the ſoul tied in the earth, is the cauſe of ſorrow; and weakneſs is the ſame, that is the character <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sambah</hi> ſtands on her ſoul intire, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth, but ſhe is cloſed and barred upward, I ſpeak as they are Hebraically wrote in their firſt Apparition: <hi>Let there be light, and it wae ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Allah Roſoli ſamat albo bonoſo raal ma ſhener ephrait ſolo monete, avar ſallu ponderah al, hoſonare raalma pedu oriko, ſoonne pelma nataras, hoſi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kod oli, deon hoſonari apaet, elma rationalem ſobat arri ſele lokatar albo, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onna ſtonus ſelat arri peke non habemus, ſobeanus ſalmoa, monita avariena, ſammat arri:</hi> Now beloved, Our brother <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhed that they could ſpeak all Languages, but interpretation is to the underſtanding to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, theſe gifts both, God hath been pleaſed to communicate to me, the unworthieſt of all men, to confound the worldly in this wiſe ſeeming ſeeing age; but never more dark in the general then now: The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is hid, the illuſtrations thereof are buried in the grave incredulity; now to awaken and enlighten the dark corners of the earth in man, is this light manifeſted in me, and the reſt of my Brethren that God is bringing to the view of the world.</p>
            <p>The derivacy from the tongues, but 'tis but one language, becauſe 'tis the major part wrote in the <hi>Tartarian</hi> tongue, in the eaſt <hi>Armenia,</hi> the third deſcent. Now a deſcent is a third refining ſince that being a tongue: For the reſtitution is reſtoring things to what they were, the Major includes the Minor in writing, though it conſiſts of many tongues, take notice of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Allab:</hi> High light is coming or riſing to the night-people, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be made day and light: for the purpoſe of God is to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeal the hidden ſecrets of darkneſs, through the manifeſtation of light, in its illuſtration, and by that light turn all into union, that is into
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170906:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>love:
<note place="margin">☟</note> Take notice there is two alls, a light all, and a dark all, and God but one all to them two alls; Light and darkneſs to him are one (I was forced to break the derivaſie by reaſon I would give you notice of two alls, light and darkneſs, and yet in their eſſential being but one all: Love is that great day that ſhall burn as an oven, for love is fire, and jelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by which God will burn up that that ſeems and is not, and by the conſumption of the one, inlet the other, and ſo bring the one all by light into himſelf, for God will utter his voyce from his Throne and that voyce ſhall ſhake terribly the earth to nothing, that he may be all: This is the extent of that language cited, but it tuns in more ſtrength in it own tongue, for the derivacy is alway weaker then the radax, as 'tis the herogliphiks of God and his creations.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 8. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſtle III.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Beloved Brethren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☟</note>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Excellency of knowledge, is to know the divine Truth, which truely none can know, but thoſe that the divine Light takes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelf: It is the eye that ſees it ſelf, and all things in it ſelf, which is God, for we have an unione with him, through one ſpirit: Now beloved having his eye, that is all things, and ſees all things as they truly are, and not as they ſeem; this ſight is deſcentive from, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn up into himſelf, that is, the Light and Life of all things, which is God, the Center, in which all things, centred do ſubſiſt, and exſiſt, and are impeaded by the ſame power.</p>
            <p>Now Beloved, God doth ſend down his declaratives through his Son Jeſus Chriſt: Now I intreat you brethren, look well, and the Lord unvail your underſtandings in this coherent diſcovery, for tis the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery that is hid in the eternal wiſdom unto this day: Minde theſe words, Chriſt ſhall come in the glory of the Father, which is the full cluſteration in the lightning the whole creation, made by himſelf: Now to know Chriſt, is eternal life: Now I beſeech you underſtand, for the knowledge here intended is perfection, which is God himſelf; for to behold Chriſt, is in truth the turning us into himſelf, and ſo into the Father by the Son, who is the Light of the Father, ſo an union is made; but this is myſterious: Now conſider what Chriſt is, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170906:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hell is, what Abaddon that deceiving Devil is, what the Fall is, what <hi>Mary</hi> is, what the Virgin is, and what death is: All theſe things will the Spirit dictate forth to our underſtandings in due time: Ye take your ſelves to be Chriſtians; can ye be his, yea know not, for Chriſt is the wiſdom of the Fathers Glory; he is the firſt and the laſt, The declarative of the Farthers Excellency, the truth of God, nay God himſelf, the demonſtratives of God are declared in and by his Son: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith the Son is the lively Image of the Father, the Text is better; reade thus, he is God, Glorious in his elluſtrations, in the Tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of himſelf: <hi>O orarau in ſalmoas in ſem anus in ſe ſapu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> O the morning peaceful Perſon in the Divine being, the wiſdom of the Father: This is one glimps of our Maſſah or Throon, or L or Chriſt: <hi>Ieſous Chriſtos in vita in ſe hominem:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt in himſelf, is the Life of men: <hi>Athra nati ſe at atti pel:</hi> He is the ſelf in the whole created: <hi>Ola ogoas aſaluat ol:</hi> He is the Light in the light world in Man: <hi>Hoſo ovallo othronia ſalem:</hi> He is the alone Peace to the created by himſelf: <hi>Hevi e en eſeu neke pele pel:</hi> He is the ſafe Rock, in the fulneſs of all things: <hi>Ova aſa ralau hoſonaret arki:</hi> He is the ſtrong rocked ſtrength in the whole creation, by himſelf: Theſe expreſſions of Chriſt, is but the outſide bark, your eye muſt ſee within that bark. Now beloved to know Hell, is to truly know Heaven; And again, to know Heaven, is to know Hell; thus to know our ſelves loſt, is truly to be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that paradiſe which is God: Now to begin, Hell is this earthly Manſion, whereon, and in we dwell: Hell is a ſeparation from happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Hell is the reſtraint from injoyment: Hell is the obſtruct of all goodneſs: <hi>Hoſs, ſe adma in rem:</hi> Tis the alone ſeparating thing from it ſelf: <hi>Non fratris ſed abbi ſelat arbe hoſonaret raalma pedit me at kad ola voſe neck habuiſe in ſem laudat abieter rone ſabat</hi> Tis the deep world in the loweſt center; tis the aſſome, bottom, abyſſe bottomleſs, tis the nothing in the thing, but an empty arie vaniſhing, in <hi>orat-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mor, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moas ſabi, atta, allah:</hi> Tis the deep heighth in the bitterneſs in morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: I beſeech you miſtake not, there is a heighth in deepneſs, as there is a deepneſs in the heighth: <hi>O allamana ſapuit,</hi> O the heighth and and depth of wiſdom is in it ſelf, that is in God, who is the all of all things: know when I ſpeak <hi>(of)</hi> tis to ſpeak to you capacities, but the ſtate in me is an other intendant.</p>
            <p>Beloved he deſcended forth, and behold we were, and are Gods eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential deſcents; thus the all things deſcended from the all, that is, thus much the creation came forth from God: thus God ſaid let it be, and behold we came forth. Now conſider whether that forth, or in, in this ſtate ſtated, be proper; for to be in God, is the Paradice in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but to be forth as is ſaid, tis a dubious word, and muſt be exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looked into; thus though we are forth from the fountain, we are in him eſſentially: Now the water in the fountain is in peace, but diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170906:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>from the fountain is trouble to the ſame that was one with the Fountain in the head, or Center, by the variety of aſcents and deſcents, that it doth encounter with, in its courſe: Now beloved in him was peace to us, nay is peace, and ſhall be peace in Glory; not that we can be greater then we were in the fountain, which is God, but our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration is to be taken into what we were, for God is no greater but ever the ſame. Now we come to the point of all points, pointing into the Center, that Center is God: Now minde I beſeech you brethren, here is the <hi>aurora ſamoas in ſem deus ſepe pauviſſe niſi nedarat:</hi> Here is the morning peace to the fainting ſoul in this low world of darkneſs; Oh! he that made all things out of himſelf, and yet he the ſame, and not the leſs nor leſſened: This is our Jehovah, this Jehovah is the firſt Perſon in the Trinity, The unfolding into the creation, is the ſecond Perſon, which is Chriſt the Son, the Glory of the Father: Now know that the Son is the light of the Father; the demonſtratives into ſtreams makes varieties, yet from that one unione, the life of thoſe varieties is God illuſtrated in the ſecond Perſon, which is Chriſt, manifeſted in fleſh, and not fleſh: I am the life of the world, them is Chriſts own proper words as the ſecond Perſon in the Trinity operative: Now the third Perſon is the produced forth from the two Perſons, that is, not <hi>vive voſa,</hi> but <hi>voſa vive;</hi> not the living voyce, but the voyce living: Look well to this diſtinction; thus the Father and the Son are one, I and my Father am one, I work, and the Father worketh: Now there is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, living voyce, and a voyce living: Thus he ſaid let there be light, and behold the ſun, the life of all things; this is the living voyce, that created all things: Now the voyce living, is the Holy Ghoſt, the third Perſon in the Trinity, which proceeded from the Father and the Son; thus the opening of the Father is the Son, the conjunct of both is the produced creation: Let us make man in our own image, that is, the Holy Ghoſt, (as you name it) but there is more inherent in that ſtate, for the Holy ghoſt in man, is the image of God, the Holy ghoſt in its Center is equal with the Father; for they three are but one in the God-head: Now to come to the original of the being of things, Thus God, the Son, the Holy ghoſt all one entire, <hi>O ſela ſapuit pecatam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ad me mekaviſſe ſelem ſam addi pedet arki all ah hoſ onneret peko oli ben:</hi> O the heavenly divine being, that reaches us into it, to declare it to us, us to it, in its origine, in its womb, in its influe, in its fulneſs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kevah auſait adki olat obediah allah hon:</hi> The evangelical operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it ſelf finding us eyes to ſee, us it, it us, both one and in one, <hi>O obuiſſe ſelat mem:</hi> O the ſeeing eye that ſees it ſelf all, we nothing that is all. Look well into this ſtate: Here ſome glimpſes you may ſee a beginning opening to the Myſtery: For the Devil or Satan that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver. To know the Devil, you muſt firſt know man, for man is the beginning, the middle, and end of the Devils work. Now what was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170906:12"/>man? I anſwer, in his firſt principle he was God; how did he fall, by coming forth, he no ſooner was, but he was not, and yet he was, by, but not in? Minde and conſider this ſtate; thus God could not make any thing greater, or gloriouſſer then himſelf, he being the fountain: Now man being come forth into the creation, there was the firſt fall: 'Tis ſaid that <hi>Lucifier</hi> was caſt down from heaven, and <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels fought with the Devil and his Angels, here lies the <hi>ſem ſapuit,</hi> the knowledge in the thing: <hi>Abuiſſe ſenarder olo ophron pero,</hi> theſe words will not be brought into Engliſh, but loſe half their ſtrength in their importance in their original exemplification, but thus much <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Angel fell, that with him many were wounded, the expreſſion is dark, ſo was light when it took darkneſs; thus that <hi>Lucifer,</hi> or Satan, or Devil, is the ſpirit in man, that is not the ſpirit of God, but by God this Devil is ſuffered. Now how this <hi>Lucifer</hi> was an Angel of light, he was in the fountain in light in God, from whom all things in their origine had their being, 'tis undeniable: Now know that man no ſooner but a Devil, there cannot be one word betwixt man and Devil, for they are one, thus the man Devil, the Devil man: Now this Angel of light here intendant is the eſſence of God in man, which fell or deſcended into earth, to imbody it ſelf in it, being imbodyed it could not be light as it was in the fountain, for deſcents muſt be from aſcents, in this ſtate here intended: <hi>Se abſat</hi> L he is the glory, glorif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing all things: Now that light deſcended, took earth and that earth became light in it ſelf, deriving light from that true light, and yet it ſelf a falſe light: Thus the Sun is the true light, the Moon is a falſe light, her ſelf as ſhe ſtands in competition with the Sun, for ſhe receives from the Sun and ſhews to us as it were her own light, and that is a falſe deceit; for when we ſay the light of the Moon (of) is proper in that ſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tis an aſſeveration, for the light from the Moon is in the Sun, and through the Moon, and not in the Moon, for nothing can properly be ſaid to be in, but that that is ſubſtantially the ſame: Now if our eyes were fully opened, then we might ſee the full ſtate, for the whole myſtery lyes in the Sun, and Moon, of which the creation ciphereth out, and are in their center herogliphicks temporal of the trines celeſtial: But to this Lucifer, this Devil, 'tis man and not man, 'tis the falſe conception in the heart in man, that is the ſpirit of man, that is the Devil; as Chriſt ſaid yea are of your father the Devil, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Satan is a deceiver, and a dweller in the heart in man, that is the ſpirit of man; But for the hell that is as the Papiſts ſay, and we ignorants ſay 'tis a lake of fire: Now I deſire to know in what world it doth center, if in the Aire, the winde would coole it, and that is light, and not utter darkneſs; If in the earth, there the cumbuſtible ſtuff can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not contain it, for fire muſt aſcend upward: O that times could hear with truth in the higheſt and deepeſt things, but they cannot I ſee by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170906:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the hintings of the ſpirit in me, and the knowledge it doth reveal unto me: <hi>Hos ſe ſapuit adma mali meded mekam ad ſe ſepit nedat oli dene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat alvah:</hi> The heigth and extent in things is to be declared, and the people are fitting to receive the ſame, but weakneſs impeads them; <hi>O alva holi ſeon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> O thou higheſt help, thy loweſt to obtain the thing which is thy ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 16. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſt. IV.</head>
            <p>THe Query inſiſted on at our laſt meeting, was held that the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual man is not God: The which Negation I deny; Thus to be ſhort: God is the Spirit, and not man; and to be ſpiritual is perfect God; we are an union with him in one: The ſame ſpirit is in us the glory of God, nay our glory; thus God hath made man his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, demonſtrating the inward life; for the life of the Creature is from within, and within is the Spirit, and that inmoſt Spirit is God in his Creature, that is Gods Spirit in Man: Now God could not dye, I anſwer No, but man muſt dye; therefore was he made, not that by his dying God could be any thing more, or any thing leſs; for he is the ſame, though we go and come, 'tis his life operating in the Creation; I ſay nothing dyes, but changes, <hi>from glory to glory,</hi> and ſo returneth to the perfection, from which perfection it came forth: Now perfection in the beginning, weakneſs in the way, perfection the end: Now in this lyes the whole concernative in the thing: Now if ye were all able to bear, what is but truth, in the point concerning Jeſus Chriſt at Jeruſalem, what he ſuffered, what it was that he ſuffered, and what he did effect by his ſufferings; The myſtery is hid to this day in that text, and all the texts coherent to that intendant, and minde the Tranſlation is rendred: to truth it is abom nable, and a monſter, and an abortive birth, becauſe the being is not centered in the truth.</p>
            <p>That Man is wholly Paſſive, the ſtate was denyed, But man is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſive in the new Creation is proved manifeſtly. Thus Man is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the caſe, or garment, in which God doth act his own will, and mans acts are a declarative of what God hath done in him: Now to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170906:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>prove God to be all in man, man nothing, 'tis eaſie to be done; but to prove man to be God is hard: becauſe the teached principle hath took ſo great an impreſſion in us, that are a teached, yet an unknowledged people; for man cannot teach God, but God doth teach man; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and teaching, theſe two be one in God, and two diſtincts in man, for 'tis God, and the called devil, 'tis Sathan, 'tis that deceiver, for 'tis the name, and not the thing, but knowledge is both the name and the thing, and that thing knowledge in its full is Jehovah, who is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; that we account knowledge, 'tis weakneſs, and in him is the all of knowledge, <hi>a ſapit arri,</hi> True light is the true diſcoverer, which is not man but God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hogoous alſo ſona in ſam ackki pele leat al:</hi> The heighth diſcoverer is Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah diſcovered, diſcovering himſelf; for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that we know not but by his Spirit, for our Spirit is enmity againſt God; now the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is himſelf, for the Spirit of God, moved, and behold the Creation. NOw to prove man God, 'tis thus: Man is a flower flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from that root that is life in it ſelf, and that life is God, the life of all things; now then you anſwered, that If God be all, and man no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then 'tis God, teaching God. No: I ſay not neither, 'tis the eternal ſpirit teaching its weak image in man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſaniel vertet al orome mem tuli eldrate naxi phele ſem in aſata alma hoſaet addad ollo ſola mem:</hi> 'Tis the God inſtructing his image in the Creation in man, and not man; This is the life of God within our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits which ſpirits being inlightned by the eternal power, 'tis the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to life viſible, and an union made with the inviſible ſpirit, it doth receive, and doth convey the thing into the heart: Now that is the Spirit of God, which in its proper eſſence is God, for know all things make not God, though that God be all things, for the things made, are but part let down from the maker, as much as to ſay a demonſtrative of God himſelf, and them in him, why then man in God, I grant it in part: Can that that made all, and by that God all conſiſts, and exiſts, and are influed, and by the ſame they are impeaded; can that properly be ſaid to have part in any thing: no 'tis all, the thing is all, that all is God; and that is part of that Gods Creation, ſo man is part of Gods Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and God is mans all. <hi>Si Ego ſoon allah avaret eckko o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ede in ſem at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar albah abſoalo mon dia tele athrat raxi ſebat arri alle neck olo ſon:</hi> Thus if I be all, how can any thing be part; there can no ſtate be ſtated to hold competency with the eternal being:
<note place="margin">☟</note> But thus man cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to be any thing, becauſe that in a moment the glory of it is withdrawn, that is the life; which life is Gods eſſence in the called thing: but to underſtand thing in its origine. There is in reality but one thing, and that one thing is God, which is the thing; and we and the whole Creation is but cifrates of that one thing, thing and no more: yet again in the terreſtial orb, counting the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, I finde man to be the chief thing amongſt the things named by the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170906:14"/>thing: I ſay God named the created things, and not <hi>Addam,</hi> for <hi>Addam</hi> came forth from God, and God demonſtrating his light and knowledge in himſelf named the created, for take your name ſpelled in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> God made man perfect, then that perfect man was perfect God; for no perfection but in Jehovah, but I know beyond that is tranſlated in that ſtate; the Spirit of roots is the rooted root: Now to come to the thing that we call man, 'tis in two parts, but divers, for the ſoul is in the body and not the body, for 'tis divine; the other part as the body you call, is humane, ſubject to weakneſſes, which the life, that is the ſoul, or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſpirit; 'tis all one intendant in this ſtate, the Spirit of man is his wiſdom, and that is properly called man, which wiſdom is but image<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and notion, and vanity, and a lye; this is mans wiſdom in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as he is deſcentive from his firſt deſcent, being united, for obedience is a tye that tyes man to God, which tye is Love: But to draw the ſtates cloſe to the view of all in a ſhort compendious method, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the full ſignificants controverted, thus the ſtate is ſtated; Man is not God, 'tis not true, for man is God, that is true; all lies in theſe words, thus; God is man, that's true, for man is not, God is true, to be true man is perfect God, for true God became perfect man, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man is true God; for perfection is reſtoration into whence we came forth.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit of man is nothing as I ſaid before, but imagery; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is not God, for God is all things, and no name, all things ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is but names and not thing; therefore not God.</p>
            <p>Here is Logick you may account it, but 'tis the heighth divinity; ſo to be ſhort, God ſpeaks to his own Spirit in us, teaches us, that is, his ſpirit brings our nothing to a conformity, for I count mans outſide, and outward actings ſhadowy and nothing.</p>
            <p>But now to come to the divine evangelical demonſtration: 'Tis love perfect, what is that? 'Tis God himſelf, creating us to act that love up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and into <hi>viva voce,</hi> in the <hi>Ecle</hi> living voice: <hi>Ecle</hi> is perfection, and 'tis an Indian word radical, and 'tis proper in that tongue derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ecleo</hi> is the proper compound word: <hi>Nox ſaggi erocloi dele mem ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bithai nelle meat arki ally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eternal perfection is clothed with all things, and is in all things and comprehends all things, and yet not ſeen, for the life of all things cannot be ſeen, felt, heard nor underſtood: This is God.</p>
            <p>Now to come to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.10. which points to this very day, as the Spirit doth dictate forth to me: Let the reſt inlightend judge, the text read from the original root in the Caldean tongue: <hi>Ouſono oon a ſabat olemus mem derata abbat a lus beneal ſabat allu phene ſolamoas inter apti ſagat mem:</hi> Take not counſel, for I will deſtroy the thing that I have made, and thereby take adventage to bring my choſen again; that is the true intent of the Spirit in them words, but it would bring in the next
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170906:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>verſe, and part of the twelfth veiſe, but in this text is the whole diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of what I affirm, and for what end God hath raiſed me up, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the world the hidden depth that lies involv'd in the inſide ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of this outſide letter; but beloved, I am but one, and the whole world againſt me, the groundſel or foundation of mans building, ſince Chriſt his time, I muſt unty their tyed ceremony, and deſtroy their foundation, and ſo a diſcovery of the everlaſting goſpel ſhall be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and received; <hi>Hoſaick alba abmon abſi ſola menderata alvah holo oon ſabdi deat al tagoas ſabin dele mem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The perfecteſt perfection is the ſtrength of the Law, the perfecteſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is the ſtrength of the Goſpel; the ſtrength of the Law is God, the ſtrength of the Goſpel is God; neither Law nor the Goſpel, for they are but names lettered out, typifying that God who is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that ſhadowy pointing out, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, The ſtrength of the Law is ſin, now what is ſin in <hi>Pauls</hi> true intent and extent? 'tis the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures weakneſs, and the weakneſs cannot be avoided by reaſon of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane clothing; the Law is weakneſs, for 'tis but the name of a thing, and not the thing; ſo the Law, and the Creation are both but Gods weakneſs, thus the Law is but name of the thing, the Creation is but name of the thing, now here they are both one.</p>
            <p>Now it remains to ſhew how theſe two names of one thing can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy one the other. The Law ſaith Do this, the humanity cannot do this the Law commands; now for not doing this, 'tis death; to what? to the name of that that is in another, ſo the Law is nothing in effect, becauſe in another; that is God: therefore the Law is death, becauſe it is name, and not thing; in doing the Law is death, becauſe it is but name and voyce of a thing; and not the thing: but the death by the Law is life in God, the doing the Law is the life in it ſelf in outward actings and not in God, <hi>ogoas in ſem albat arri neelet me erko al ſabbat ar ſiat al;</hi> The Law is death to life, the life is death to the Law; they both dead in themſelves, that they may be, nay they are alive both in God; for God taking up his lettings down, that is man, and the Law; for Law and man is one in him; nay, in their eſſencied eſſence, for they came from God, and are taken into God through Chriſt, then there is neither man, nor Law; they are both made one by the Goſpel, which is peace, love, Chriſt, God, Jah, Jehovah; Now where is your riddle of Law to be ridled out? 'tis for want of knowledge, that the bondage of the Law lies ſo hard on and upon the Creation,
<note place="margin">☟</note> for the Law to light is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and man to knowledge is ignorance, ſo both one; the Goſpel is light, and that cauſes ignorance to paſs away; but 'tis not the name Goſpel, but 'tis the Goſpel named thing that works this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O agallo moon ſabi alle neck ſedit arri pele mem arbat al alſane mem.</hi> The divine truth is the true diſcoverer in the depth of Myſtery, for our eyes reaches not the living center: Now know Brethren, that God that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170906:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath let down to us his glorious invitations, eiphered out by alluring words, minde it is but Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovah converſing with his Son in the humane nature, or with his Angel in fleſh, for we are the vegetables of the Deity tied to himſelf by the Angel in us, for our Angel converſes with him: Now an Angel is the true diſcover of us to God, God to us, and the unione Maker with God, the Cavenanter with God, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanter with man, the both, the one, the all, that is, God converſing with himſelf in the humanity by his ſpirit in us, we in it; Minde that ſtate.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 24, 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſtle V.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe word of the Lord came unto me upon the ſeventeenth day being Munday at four a clock in the morning, and did command me to write: <hi>Addam</hi> I keep your ſtate, though my intention is another name, and thing; but for your diſpute and conteſt, here is ſatisfaction, that God hath been pleaſed to diſcover unto me. I beſeech you minde, for this Myſtery is not yet revealed to the ſons of men. The Apoſtles themſelves were ignorant in this Myſtery, that you are ye think ſo perfect in: You ſhall ſee they knew it not, elſe they would have declared it, in ſome one place or other. Now you are ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that every one knows it, but the wiſdom of God is onely the confounding of man, and ſo to bring him unto himſelf: Now minde, <hi>Addam</hi> you ſay was man, ſo ſay I, with the woman, for know that a man is not a man without the woman; for they two are but one fleſh nay one ſpirit, if they be once brought to be man: Now man being deſcended from his firſt principle which was God, know that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent muſt be ſub under the aſcent, and man is Gods deſcent: Now the very being created, was a fall, you cannot deny, for created muſt be the workmanſhip of the Creator, this cannot be denied: Now man was made, you hold man to be one man as we account, I ſay mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of men, and women; for underſtand the diſtarings of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for a million is to him but one; all that was, and is, and is to come, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea but one man: I let the Query lye in your own name <hi>Addam.</hi> Now his deſcent forth was a fall, but we muſt underſtand that ſtate was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170906:15"/>becauſe innocent (minde I intreat) Now to be innocent is the ſtate that God ſtated man in; Now knowledge is the fall, and I prove know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be the reſtoration, thus weakneſs is mans accounted knowledge, but that that man accounts to be is not, for tis nothing, and nothing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be knowledge, for God is all knowledge, and man as we account man no knowledge, for man is a vain thing, and a vain thing cannot be knowledge, but God is knowledge, and all things are in him: Now this point will open way to diſpute, but I would bar it out, you will ſay, if all things are in him, why then ſin is in God: I beſeech you minde, ſin is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, therefore not in him: thus, tis the invention in man, that is not in God, for as man is a deſent from God, ſo there may be properly ſaid to be deſents from man; Now to be deſents in man, it turns him from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God like, in his eſſential being, for God made him one, and he not content in being one he became multiplicity, but it was in imagination, and that overthrew him and us; for the wiſdom of man is creating all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways falſe creatives, which is like God but 'tis not God, and yet ſits in the ſeat of God, this is mans ſpirit, lift up by himſelf out of its cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Now <hi>Addam</hi> in this firſt deſent was happy, becauſe innocent; Now how became he unhappy? in not being innocent, what was the cauſe he loſt that ſtate innocency? it was ſeeming knowledge, that was a falſe conception in the heart; what was the garden? it was God his command to be obeyed in love: Look well brethren, for <hi>Addam</hi> was no more then you are, if yea Be, minde that B, in that lies the myſtery; The garden was not a place fenced in, but it was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that man ought to have obeyed, then it gave fruit that was life, but diſobedience threw men out from the command, then man became a wanderer: Minde in your ſelves, how doth love tye you to obedience? how doth hate untye that that love hath tyed, judge ye. Now to finde this ſerpent, that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> 'tis the Devil, turned into an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light, it was no created thing that ticed <hi>Eve,</hi> neither was <hi>Eve</hi> ticed, but the man and woman are accounted one in that ſtate, for the woman is the glory of the man; why <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid ſo, and he and I know ſo; thus God made man and woman, not as that ſtory ſaith, of a rib of the man, I deny that: Now you will ſay I deny the Scripture, I ſay no; Firſt prove you that to be the Scripture, and then you are able to erect your ſentence: but let me tell you both in the Old and New Teſtament, I ſee too much of the ſerpentine knowledge, invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in with the divine Truth; for where light in the intendant ſpirit was repealed, man by his wiſdom would connex, and ſo on to make his nothing ſomthing, and indeed by ſo doing, hath indeavored to make that that was not, to be: Now what is the woman intended in that ſtate, 'tis the creation of God, what is the man, 'tis Chriſt, that is the true intendant as the Lord lives, and fancy what you will, till you come to this center, you are loſt. Thus the creation of God is the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170906:16"/>declaration of himſelf, in earthly voyces and ſemblances, or hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicies temporal of the Deity celeſtial: Chriſt is the glory of God, the wiſdom of God, the ſtrength of God: Now God let down the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by, and through, and in Chriſt, that is the ſtrength of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed through Chriſt into the creation, and by the ſame ſtrength, that is Chriſt, will God reſtore his faln creation, and the creation reſtored is Chriſts Bride, and his glory, ſo the creation reſtored is the glory of the man, which is Chriſt, the Son of the living God: This is the true intent of the intention in that hieroglyphicie, in <hi>Addam</hi> and <hi>Hevah.</hi> But to come to the tractat declarative, declared, which is <hi>Addam</hi> and <hi>Eve: Addi ſele localis in ſem abbiuiſſe ſelemus abdi ſelat ori aſabat arri:</hi> The <hi>Addam</hi> is <hi>Eve,</hi> and the <hi>Eve Addam,</hi> both one in fleſh and ſpirit, in me their ſpirit and life: <hi>Ory ſabie ſelat arri nedat merki allat maby ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus abde ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gat ally penat ori apaet nedet me:</hi> The beginning was the fall, the end the reſtoration, the depth heighth, the heighth depth, God all, and in all things, for the eſſential being in things, is God declared in voyces, and ſemblances, and the creation created is Gods hieroglyph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ie: So now <hi>Addam</hi> and <hi>Hevah</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is her proper name, and her derevacie is from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heth,</hi> that is from God, <hi>Heth</hi> is Gods ſtrength, <hi>Hevah</hi> is the created by God: Look into the ſtate of them two Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in their hieroglyphicie, now look into their pronounciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Heth, Hevah; Heth</hi> is one pronounciation, <hi>Hevah</hi> is two: Now if you could but underſtand them two Characters, they are the creation in God, for know God cannot be God, but by declared creatings, nor the creation in God, but by him in it, here is the myſtery of myſteries, you cannot ſpake God but in the creation, and that creation is himſelf in himſelf, for he is the life and continuance, in his created by him in him, and to him: Minde and do not ſtudy diſputes, for here is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of minding, not of diſputing; I beſeech ye, that if any be diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for Maſteries, ſtate your ſtate, and I will anſwer in writing, or I will give the ſtate in writing, and if you can anſwer, I ſhall ſubmit to judgement.</p>
            <p>Now the being made in innocency, how came they to be tempted? it was from within, for though the allurements are, as we think from without, 'tis within: Now as 'tis read God made the Serpent, 'tis ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly falſe, for then he laid the ſnare, and who could eſcape, being he created all, and he put enmity betwixt the ſeed of the woman and the Serpent: Now what was this Serpent? his hieroglyphick was the beaſt, that was indued with wiſdom, above any thing in the material creation, next under man, and he tempted the woman; and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, that man that lieth with any beaſt ſhall be put to death, here is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſobeying, produced from the falſe conception in the heart, for ſhe taſted the forbidden fruit of knowledge, but the deluſion was from within, in not obeying, and <hi>Addam</hi> he was tempted by her to act things
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170906:16"/>not convenient: So the creation became vain in their uninnocent actings: Still the Devil is within, that is the deceiving heart in man, is always hatching his own deformity: The Angels that fell, were the Light of God in our innocent ſtate, eclipſed by our fall; for an Angel is light, light an Angel, this Angel in us is faln from to be reſtored to the center, they fell from, that is, into God by Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Angel of the everlaſting Covenant, he is <hi>Chogoas ſola ſol,</hi> he is the high alone riſing Sun: <hi>Hezeche el parat attah eſaboyne ſabat allah occare,</hi> he is the beams illuſtrating Gods excellency in his full creations: <hi>Sabbah al,</hi> holy, or high holy, this is the Angel of the Covenant: Now an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel is God, and the Sons of God are his Angels, that is, the Light of God in man, is Gods Angel in man: An Angel is refined man, or man unbodied or unvailed, for vailing is a fall, becauſe tis not capable of the glory it dwelt in before imbodyed, or invailed and our Angels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his face in glory, this is an alluſive ſpeech to <hi>Peter,</hi> our Angel or his Angel: 'Tis thus, an Angel in Commiſſion, then he can do what God doth pleaſe, as to deſtroy multitudes, but in his operative courſe, he is the convertor, and converfor with his fellow-Angels in us men and women: We are come unto the innumerable company of Angels, in <hi>rem ſopience</hi> in the wiſdom in the thing: <hi>O ovallo in ſamoas in ſepe pauviſſe ſem allat ori deni potarum ablah ſolamus in ſo ſoollah abbi ſelorum agoaus a pater orbis ſelat appi ſele oramus in ormoous in ſe ſola:</hi> The vigor in the thing, is the life of the thing, and the thing is in it ſelf one thing, and that one thing all things, and all Times, and Titles, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, and Trophies, and Conqueſts, Advantage, and Death, and Life, and Mortality, and Immortality and all things, and the thing nothing: This is the thing in things, and it ſelf nothing, and out of that nothing all things came forth, this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heth</hi> God, Jeſus, or Chriſt, that cannot fall or leſſen, he is always the ſame; this is the true deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy from the tongues into Engliſh.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſtle VI.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Belove,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Divine and Evangelical being is in God, from which foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain we iſſued forth, by the ſtrength of God in the declarative of his Son; for the Son is the Father, and the holy Ghoſt is the product, and he is the Father in the firſt Center, but he is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170906:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>operating in the creation, nay the life of the Creation, for he is perfect truth, and perfect truth is perfect God (minde the ſtate) There is a perfect truth in every created Creature, which is the eſſential being of God in the ſame; for that that is not cannot be properly nor unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to be any thing, for know, that truth muſt be truth and admit no negotiation, but muſt be it ſelf, and that ſelf taken into it ſelf,
<note place="margin">☟</note> is perfect God; Now man he is the Lye as we account him man; for we account and name weakneſs capable of ſorrow man; That is the Lye, for 'tis accounted for the thing, and is not the thing, as man accounts it: Now to be man is truth, and drawn up to his center, is perfect God, in his firſt perfection, minde, perfect man is perfect Chriſt, Chriſt is God; Now know that man is nothing, till he be in Chriſt, now when is that, when we are centred in him who is our man, and we are but names till then, but he it is that made us names, that is, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and he it is that makes us things, one thing in himſelf, and one in God, through the everlaſting Covenant: what is that? tis the mercy of God himſelf, that is Chriſt, minde that indraft, for to ſpeak the Deity proper, tis unione, that is Jehovah: Declaratives are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as you call them, which is but the heighth of motion of Jehovah: Now know that God and Chriſt is all one, ever was and to come the the ſame: Now Chriſt promiſed was God himſelf, that would take the life of the world into a more near living life into himſelf, by illuſtrating himſelf in the beams of words, they being let down to allure his people, which inſide ſpirit of them outſide ſpellings, or words is, Jeſus the Son of God; for the life of Jeſus is the declarative of God in the life of our life, for there is a natural life and a ſpiritual life: Now you are alive in Chriſt, when your ſelf is dead unto your ſelf, and his power raigns and rules in you, and ye are ruled by it wholy, then ye live, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye are dead though living, for if we live tis being one, in the unione: Minde well, and you may diſcern the baſis on which the Scripture the truth of it is founded; for I deny all to be inſerted in the book called Scripture, to be true; for in the main point of the new Teſtament, is ſtated the Lye for the truth, that is, the outſide man, for the anointing or inſide ſpirit, as I ſhall open: Now brethren by creation, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny, brethren by reſtoration, to you, to all, to one and every one, is this my Meathod laid down, not to perſwade any or all, but to the quick-headed and unknowledge-hearted: I know what I ſpeak, and again to the heart-knowledged, whoſe receptacle or knowledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides there, that in that ſtrength, hath brought not onely the head to go out from the heart, but hath brought the actions to be witneſſes, what is done by the Spirit of God in the heart. Now theſe two ſtates will hold all people, for there is but light and darkneſs in the Creation; Now minde and all ſtand upon your own Center, whilſt I open this vailed, vailed, and vailed Vail, that is, the Divinity, buried with the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170906:17"/>Heads, and Hands, and Tongues, and Pens of Humanity: Chriſt was promiſed that he ſhould come, and reſtore faln man; what was that? It was reſtoring the buried Divinity up in the humanity, that is, Chriſt in us the hope of Glory, for without Chriſt no hope, nay, no glory, he is our glory, and he is the gathering us into himſelf; then gathered we are in ſtrength, and ſtrength is man, man is Chriſt, and Chriſt is God: So then there the beginning hath taken its end into it ſelf, ſo an unione in one, that one is God. Now know that Chriſt is God, God is Chriſt, both one, the product are we. Now minde, <hi>Selat ori alter arbe opat mem ſiddei ſem arbat al ogo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oon addi nex homo:</hi> The eternal purpoſe was reconciliation in himſelf by man, not man, both God and man, and neither God nor man. Here lyes the unridled myſtery, that lyes hid from the world, I beſeech you minde,
<note place="margin">☟</note> for 'tis not my voyce that is here uttered, 'tis the eternal ſpirit dictating forth unto you its own inſtruction, to cauſe your vailed ignorance to taſte death, by the living life offered unto you, in its tranſcendeant life: <hi>Allu ſaba ar dele mem ſelos in re facit me</hi> (minde:) I am the high living reſt to the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thing, that is man and the creation: <hi>Selos abbi a ſalmoas in re fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſere ad amalam orbeus ſabat al:</hi> The high denomination of God in man, is the reſting in wiſdom in himſelf, that is, God. This ſtate is dark, but 'tis true, for the beginning and middle are brought to center in the end, that is, God: Now know that Chriſt created the world, he is the life of the world, the creation is Chriſts ſpouſe; know that the humanity is but the caſe, for the divinity to act and operate in; Now how could he that was the life of all things, made all things, and by him all things did, do, and ſhall conſiſt, and ſubſiſt, how could he dye? <hi>vox populos in ſem alba arri nedet erko on:</hi> The peoples voyce in the thing, is not the true thing; for know that the proper humanity could not dye, for then the whole creation muſt dye at once, neither the life of the Creator could not be confined (in one) that was and is all; now let me ſpeak truth, he died not, he ſuffered not, he ſinned not, he ſaved not by any act that was done; for tis the Prieſts trade from the Popiſh deſcent: Chriſt hath been the great Prieſts market, they have bought and ſold him, they got the name and knew not the thing. But to ſtate the text, Its origine was Latine, theſe words, <hi>ver non homo, ſed in loca paucaveret:</hi> A man not a man, but in place of offence: The Text in the <hi>Chaldean</hi> tongue, <hi>Alla alarum in ſam ſagaus ſab,</hi> the meaning is the ſame with the Latine Text: The true Greek Text in his firſt origine, <hi>Ous te ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramon in ſem ſeala alar ophrone adriei ſebat:</hi> The Hebrew in the root, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Hebrew in word, <hi>ack ack L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>addi ne,</hi> that is, he is, and is not the God; the Hebrew Text will not admit no more bending to illuſtrate the ſtate, for to hold the truth in the truth of word, it will not couch to your minde or will; for minde and will muſt yield to the word. I beſeech you think on that laſt ſtate ſtated, for tis the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170906:18"/>divine truth: Now to begin or enter into this <hi>alyſo</hi> or deep ſea, I intreat you minde, one Text ſaith, <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the ſerpents head:</hi> Minde that Text, I prove that falſe, and the Scripture is true: So I deny not the Scripture, but the Lye that is added to, or ſet for Scripture. Now I ſhall declare how you may know I know it to be the Scripture, and I tell you how you ſhall know it to be the Scripture; Thus, when the life of Jeſus is your life, and your ſpirit taken into that Spirit that wrote the Scripture, who is, and none elſe, the true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitor of his own intendants: Minde them words, the intent of the ſpirit was in that falſe tranſlated text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hevah,</hi> for know that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is <hi>Hevah,</hi> which is weakneſs, that is the woman, for the creation is the weak woman of God, and Chriſts ſpouſe; The truth that lyes vailed in that Text, or Lye, I count it no better, neither is it: Now the truth that lyes vailed, the intendant in that Text is, the ſtrength of the woman ſhall overcome weakneſs, which you account ſin. Now who is the ſtrength of the creation: is not Chriſt? for till you are in Chriſt, you are woman, that is weakneſs; in Chriſt you are man, that is, a ſtrong conquerer through him who is the ſtrength of the woman, the woman and man one in him, that is, Chriſt: The next is, <hi>A Virgin ſhall conceive and bring forth her firſt born, and they ſhall call his name</hi> Emanuel, I give you this, though the Text doth not hold in full; what is this? the intendant is Chriſt: Who is this Virgin? it was not <hi>Mary,</hi> and it was <hi>Mary,</hi> that you have confined Chriſt to be born of, Tis the ſpirits intent, the whole birth, born, and brought forth in the whole creation, was, is, and to come the ſame; this is <hi>Mary,</hi> that is, perfection, for where Chriſt is born, a pure Virgin doth conceive and bring forth, for he himſelf is Virgin, birth, and bringer forth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Now you whoſe reaches are tied to the traduced, not underſtood letter, called Goſpel, or word of God, you begin to ſwell: Let not ſwelling turn to rage, but deſire knowledge of him who is the true Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitor of his own intendants. Now to come to your name Chriſt, confined to Jeruſalem: I am a Jew of the Tribe of <hi>Ruben,</hi> begotten by the Goſpel, by the life of Jeſus Chriſt, Jah, Jehovah, L, Emanuel, a One, <hi>Tele, Thre-on, Pell, Sanah, Eloah, Ad, Eval, Allu, Haſo, Apal, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, On, Sele, Tran,</hi> All theſe names in their Tongues and Languages the ſame, and but one name, that is, God or Chriſt, both one, one both. I ſay the man Chriſt ſuffered as you ſay, ſo ſay I, you underſtand not, that do I: <hi>Chriſt was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>was put to death, ſuffered by the hands of wicked men, roſe from the dead, deſcended into hell,</hi> would you have any more? I acknowledge all this. Saith one Text, <hi>He ſitteth at the right hand of God, and maketh interceſſion for us,</hi> That I deny, and charge it blaſphemy; but before I prove the blaſphemy, know them words is the ſealed book, not opened yet; therefore minde I beſeech you for Jeſus ſake (that is your own word and my ſpirit) mark that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170906:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtate. To begin with the firſt, that I have declared, Chriſt was put to death, and ſuttered by ſinners, here lies the ridled riddle: Firſt, Chriſt created all things, is the life of all things, he could not dye, for with him the whole creation, nay God himſelf, in that ſtate it muſt ſtand thus for the divinity of Chriſt: Secondly, the humanity of Chriſt could not dye, thus, if the humanity muſt dye, then the whole altogether, the whole creation, no part left nothing, nor no earth, for that is Chriſts humanity, as well as we. Now know you hold that Chriſt muſt be perfect God, ſo ſay I, then know that two perfections at once cannot be, that is to ſay, two Gods, for names make not things, but things make names, there muſt be a living thing before a name; there is another Myſtery, one of the greateſt in the Scripture. Know my learning is not of man, nor by man, but I am taught of the living God, who is the true Expoſiter of his own intendants. <hi>He deſended in hell;</hi> where was that coyned? at <hi>Rome,</hi> from the Papal diabolical doctrine, the Panther that is a deſtroyer ineagling is quick catched, and the carrying the Ty, or catched into that fatal place. The ſpirits denomination was, the <hi>Panther,</hi> or the ineagling the Tye into that fatal place, the ſtate was let down to me in them words at firſt, I cannot reach it, my manhood yet, for know he that created all things, was all things, and is all things; how can he be ſaid to go into any local place? for the intendant Jeſus muſt deſcend into one place, but Jeius muſt deſcend into Hell, what is that? that deſcent is into us, who are Hell or Devils, for ye are of your father the Devil, what is the Devil? he is not love: then you know what is the contrary in man, Chriſts deſcent into Hell was to redeem us, tis true in the intendant, for know they and we are but one ſpirit, he deſcendeth now into us, as he did then into them; for his deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into our Hell, is his own reſurrection in us, in him, by one the very ſame ſpirit, if the ſpirit of Jeſus be in ye, ye are riſen from death to life; ſo ſaith the true Scripture. But now to that Text that ſaith, <hi>He ſitteth at the right hand of God, and maketh interceſſion for us,</hi> I charge it to be abſolute blaſphemy: Thus God is one in the unione his Deity, glorifie me with the glory that I had with thee, before the world was: There was but one God, is but one God, one glory in himſelf, that is to ſay himſelf in himſelf. Can one God intercede to another? no, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath God hands, neither any fear, neither any place, for he is all and nothing, this is God: Now for you to ſpeak God truly, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; for thus the all of the creation, the beauty, ſtrength, wiſdom, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and knowledge cannot ſpell his name: All named together is his name, that ſpell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ehovah <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Thus Chriſt died not, he ſuffered not, he ſinned not, he ſaved not, by any act that was done, for the life of all things could not ſuffer, which was his divine eſſence, the humanity could not dye, then the whole creation, and God himſelf, for if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the ſubſiſtance be taken away, the ſubſiſtance is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170906:19"/>dead, for the humanity is all things, the divinity the life of all things, and they cannot be ſeparated; Chriſt is the life of God, and if the creature can deſtroy the Creator which is the life of it ſelf, judge ye, it may cauſe its own likeneſs to ſuffer, that is, a part of the humanity of Chriſt; ſo Chriſts body being part of the humanity of God, it ſuffered as man, and no more, for he was the tranſcendant pipe, in which the Deity paſſed through, to illuſtrate the will of his own commandings; he was the firſt birth of the brethren, the anointed above his fellows, that was ſpiritual, that could not ſuffer undeniably; For know if God could ſuffer, then he is no God, but man, he ſaved not by any act that was done, for minde, the acts of humanity cannot ſatisfie divinity: or thus, the obedience of man, cannot ſatishe God, for then you would make God weakneſs, as you are weakneſs, ſo by conſequence, you are as great a God as the eternal being, which I deny, and you will not affirm for the ſpirit of Jeſus (look to your own ſtate) Jeſus is a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, a Saviour cannot ſuffer, for then no Saviour; minde and the Lord give you underſtanding. For if he could be angry, no God, for anger is weakneſs, that is, in us, not in God, if he ſhould but think at ſuch a time he would ſatisfie himſelf for the ſins of the people, then that thought makes him no God, but do you know that you were, when you were not that that now you are, and ſhall be? God is unchangable, for know that which we account to be, is not, and that we account not to be, that is, for though we be dark in our ſelves, we are light in him, and when we are light in our ſelves, then is our greateſt darkneſs; thus God doth ſtain the glory of man, you muſt be captivated by his love, that is, your reſtoring to life, for in this main ſcope of ſcripture (for want of knowledge) is the Nations loſs, that God may have mercy, for they have ſtated the humane body, God, to ſuffer to the divine Deity, God, when it is but one very thing, for the divinity and humanity make up perfection, and that is God in unione, and we have made them by accounting two Gods, hanging one in another: The word is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per according to your own riddle. <hi>Ox te ſabdi el dele mem,</hi> The God is alone all in all things; minde that ſtate well: So minde theſe two ſtates: <hi>Selos in rem a ſabar:</hi> the heavenly thing cannot ſuffer: <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitas in rem ſaddi ne:</hi> The humanity could not ſatisfie for the thing: <hi>O a palaram in ſam madaous in ſelous in aberemus ſoas alah al:</hi> The high living light could not ſuffer to it ſelf. So that riddle of bondage to the creation is unridled, if underſtood and believed, that is, my Gods work, and not mine, for my work is <hi>alah al,</hi> to unſeal the hidden myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the Scriptures, added by mans invention, and falſe conſtruction, and when this is done, Behold and ſee, for I <hi>Theaurau John</hi> did behold and have ſeen the precious pearl, the ſouls delight, O the Apples of life that my ſoul thirſts after! oh the paradaical fruit, <hi>O ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ah halalujah al,</hi> oh the divine being is the inraviſhment of the ſoul, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170906:19"/>injoyment in the paradaical eſſence! <hi>O amorum in ſobao; ſe,</hi> O the the lovely divine being is in it ſelf! O the pictures of gold, in apples of ſilver! O the perfume in Paradice is the injoyment of himſelf! O beloved, our lovelineſs is there! But my brother <hi>John</hi> ſaw the new <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> deſcend, what is that, it is to attract our ſouls to its lovely center, this is the time that the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be letten down, which is the light and knowledge in the everlaſting Goſpel, they ſhall all know me, how? they ſhall all be taught of God, that teaching is knowledge, that knowledge is God; the new Heaven, the new Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs; for where knowledge lays the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Jeſus Chriſt erects his Throne: <hi>O a ſaba ormoas ſabdial.</hi> O reſt to wiſdom, wiſdom reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſtle VII.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE diſagree in names, and not in things; For thus we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the natural man, when the Scripture calls the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al man, that is to ſay, man riſen out of the corruptible eſtate, for now man is man in tearm or name, accounted by man; that is, in the account of his own figures, for we are figures one of another; and a one figure of the Deity by Creation: this is the outward figure man, but the in-being figure, is the life of this outward figure; and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of that is God in us: which is in Scriptures called man, or the image of God, or the Trinity in man, figurative, which figure, nay which life is God, Jeſus our Saviour: For to give a narration of that whole conteſted for, not underſtood, for underſtanding cauſes conteſts and diſputes to ceaſe, that's concerning man fallen from light to darkneſs, and man reſtored from darkneſs to light: what do you underſtand by the ſealed book? there lies ſomething to be declared, that is the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Goſpel to be preached; this the word holds forth: Now what is this, but a greater diſcovery to us, of the light of God in us; men and women, that thereby we may diſcern and know the myſtery of the ſealed book, which is the Scripture or word of God, as you call it, to unvail the vailed truth that lies hid and buryed by mans invent on, and that lye took off; and then that truth in its firſt purity intire, inſerted with illuſtration of it, and the connexion of that truth, that God is a bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170906:20"/>forth in man; for ye ſhall all be taught of me ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now here is ſtated the high myſtery of all, that hath been ſo conteſted for in the world, ſince man was, 'tis ſhort, but minde I beſeech you, for the myſtery is all in the thing, and the Spirit muſt guide you to the true light of the diſcovery, diſcovered, <hi>Nos ſe exce in meam gloria adoramus:</hi> We in him did behold his glory, and did worſhip; this was before we came forth into beſtial bodies, to which text holds this declarative, it is imbodied in them words; when the Angels praiſed me and ſang toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jobs</hi> words: This was before a viſible Creation.</p>
            <p>Now thoſe angels fell, the word will hold with the original thus, they fell becauſe they deſcended into Vegitables, and left their firſt habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Here is the myſtery, how did they loſe their firſt ſtate? They diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the command, what was that? Love: for the duty of heavenly injoyment is love in perfection. Now they detracted from that; how could Angels detract? as it was a Creature, yet purely the life of them eſſenced in the Creator, for though the life of them was eſſenced in God by acts Evangelical, yet detracting; for know there is a motion in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſtate or thing, but that one of which, all the Creation are but ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances: He ſtands, and all the Creations move, and their motion is their homage due to God by Creation, yet the life of all them are eſſenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in God: Now the detraction cauſed a diminution of that glory they poſſeſſed in that ſtate. And do you, and all the people and Nations know, that that way is, and them Angels became men, and that was <hi>Addam</hi> in the Garden, though eſſenced in God ſtill.</p>
            <p>Now my <hi>Hamah</hi> holds more full, and an unione ſtate, Now the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels fallen created them bodies to act in, as fleſhly bodies to act in, proved from this text: The Sons of God came in to the daughters of men, and ſaw them beautiful: Now how was that? it was thus: the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them did aſſume unto themſelves a comlineſs, that was but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that text makes this forth, for they ſowed fig-leaves to cover their nakedneſs with, that is the truth: and God himſelf is witneſs: Now you will ſay man made himſelf: I intreat you minde, if I am eſſencied in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is acts of my own from that eſſency, as I am a deſcent, deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from that eſſential eſſence, which is God himſelf: ſtill know mans detraction is in himſelf, abſolutely free: onely the life of the being is eſſenced in God: Well, now when theſe Angels were imbodied in fleſh, a command came from that eſſence, that is to ſay from the Lord Creator, to his firſt, ſecond, and third deſcent: Look now here is work, none but the livened, or living by, and in the new living life of God can reach this high myſterious truth, which ſtile is the Trinity in the humanity. Now this Law was weak, in an equal ballance, ballancing the Creature, and it ſelf, juſt, juſt, juſt, to deſtroy one another, to ſave both. Now this was the called Chriſt or God, which by illuſtrating in light, into the inviſible principle, to cauſe a reſurrection of himſelf, or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170906:20"/>as you ſay, his image in us, to a living life in himſelf; This is <hi>Mary,</hi> this is Jeſus, and no other: for know there remains the true figure of the Trinity in man, that cannot be defaced quite; that is the tye in man to God, as ſoveraign: and that tye in man, looks for mercy, from that ſoveraign, which is thus much, the tye acknowledges digreſſion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened is remiſſion, that is Chriſts reſurtection in us, this is Chriſt and no other, which is Gods mercy taking us into himſelf; and then an unione is made: for beloved, be not ſo ſtupid in this point, to think that God could die, or ſuffer, for know, you all know the ſoul is chief, and that ye ſay never dyes, but is in joy, or ſorrow. Now you ſtate this name Jeſus to be a Saviour, what a madneſs if duly conſidered, it is, To think that a Saviour could die! then your Saviour is leſs then your own ſoul, ſo then by this rule your ſoul is a greater Saviour, then he that ſhould ſave you.</p>
            <p>Thus brethren, the ſame thing, according to your belief, being mans lye, I beleeved it, ſtood for it, but when the Lord came upon me in power, and called me to the Miniſtry of his truth, he ſmote me dumb, blinde, and dead; and my ſufferings were unexpreſſible: then I ſaw the ſufferings of the body of that man Jeſus, my brother.</p>
            <p>Now let me tell you, many men ſuffer more then he did. I beſeech you minde, I ſpeak truth; let not received opinion delude you, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God to enlighten you, that you may ſet your ſpirit upon the truth of the thing, and not be deceived by the name; which holds nothing, but the thing is the life of God, the mercy of God taking you into it, this is Jeſus our Saviour, the ſon of the eternal God.</p>
            <p>Brethren, that I ſpeak here, I ſhall declare to the whole world; and all things I ſpeak is ſet down in writing, and I am ready and do deſire, that the whole Aſſembly of Divines, if they pleaſe to except againſt any point, If I prove not by the true Scripture, confounding the falſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie of men, inſerted in the book called Scripture, I am willing to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; I deſire no more favour. And from this day know I am not mad, as they have accounted me; but 'tis the blindeneſs in them, that counts it madneſs in me.</p>
            <p>The name Jeſus hath deceived the Nations, taken from this word in Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Maſſah,</hi> which heighth of expreſſion is thus much in the full, 'tis the all-ſaving, the all, his things, this is the true text as the Lord lives, from Maſſah.</p>
            <p>That text with this text, <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head; And a vigin ſhall conceive and bring forth.</hi> Now let me ſay, that both <hi>Mary</hi> and Jeſus is both perfect names, but Jeſus is no name, but the thing of things; he is the life, glory, excellency of the Father; He is the Father, and the Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as you call them; but calling doth not confirm it to be ſo, for many a time a falſe name is put upon a true thing. But I beſeech you brethren, let me ſpeak truth to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170906:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>you, for I cover after you, not yours: I preach not to prey upon you, that is to inrich my ſelf by conſtraint from you, as too many of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolical dumb dogs, Tythe-mongers I mean, do, for they miſunderſtand this text, <hi>Feed my people,</hi> and inſtead of feeding, they fleece the people; to your ſhame the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as you call it, to you I ſpeak, for doing is the true demonſtrative of what we are in Chriſt; for know we in <hi>England</hi> have got the name Jeſus in our mouth, which is a lye unto us, for doing is Jeſus, for <hi>not be that heareth my words, but he that doth what I command,</hi> he is Chriſts diſciple.</p>
            <p>Now let me tell you brethren, our Saviour in the moſt of us, lies too high in us; the word is proper thus, Chriſt in the head is a lye, without being in the heart; that is to ſay in curious terms and names, but without action from the heart, 'tis a lye, and nothing, but a dead vaniſhing; but if Jeſus be in you, ye are riſen from death to life, how is that? thus, the head hath loſt the ſtrength of the name, and the hands from the heart, by declaring, diſtributing acts of love, and relief to the neceſſity of the poor, that is the thing; there is not one among you but is a namer of Jeſus, but how few are ye, that do as he hath commanded? Brethren, till ye be doers, ye are a lye, and are deceived, your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of the devil; for ye name Jeſus to effect another end, but love is Jeſus acting, by a living diſtributing life, to his members.</p>
            <p>But let me tell you, there is a day of vengeance a coming from the Lord to try all fleſh, and purge all droſs; and then the door ſhall be glorifyed, and the ſayer or lyer ſhall be tormented.</p>
            <p>Now this in the preſence of God, and his elect Angels, I can ſpeak in truth of heart; I have coveted no mans gold or ſilver, nor nothing; though ſince the Lord hath called me to preach, and declare the truth, in the everlaſting Goſpel, no mans breach, and ſuffering like mine, both in body, and eſtate, yet I joy, becauſe I know my work ſhall be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is I know, multitudes of people, are to be gathered by my miniſtry, before the great overflowing ſcourge come.</p>
            <p>Beloved, all things below himſelf, and my work in him, to declare to you the people, that the Lord will deliver out of bondage, is doing to me, all things to me; (but love to you received from him) is dead, and not eſteemed of by me. O my ſoul is drawn into that fountain of love, which is God; and from thence being thereby enlighned, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all things at a true value, for before we are enlightened, we value things not as they are, but as they ſeem, and ſo are deceived; for we account that to be which is not in truth, and then nothing.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>Revelation,</hi> when he let down the myſterious myſtery, his eye reached us, and this day we are in; for he ſaid that the everlaſting Goſpel ſhould be preached, which is the love of God: but in ſuch a powerful manner, that it ſhould turn all things up, and down, to make an inlet for it ſelf; And know, ſufferings brings man to ſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170906:21"/>and the lifted up fatteth for the day of ſlaughter, which Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaw, when he had wrote this book, called the <hi>Revelation of God.</hi> Now mind there is not one, of all the reſt, was ſo high for myſtery, as he was, and yet his, is called the Revelation, which is meant, a declaring cleerly to the underſtanding of men; now if that be the Revelation, what is the myſtery? the myſtery is the Revelation, the Revelation the myſtery; ſo the everlaſting Goſpel is the true diſcoverer both of hiſtory and myſtery.</p>
            <p>Thus I <hi>John</hi> ſaw, what was that? I <hi>Theaurau-John</hi> ſaw, what <hi>John</hi> ſaw. Now minde, <hi>The,</hi> is from the Greek word <hi>Theos,</hi> a compound; now <hi>The</hi> ſtands before in my name given by God, which is to ſay the eye, or Gods eye; diſcovering the light, in the hidden myſterious my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>John.</hi> For know, 'tis Gods eye that muſt give light, and ſight of his own intendants.</p>
            <p>Brethren, let me ſpeak; you know not me: I am in you, ye know it not; I am your life, and ye underſtand it not, nor what I ſpeak. From this very expreſſion, is forged the humanity of Chriſt to be very God, when the truth is, the ſpeech is ſpoken by the inſide ſpirit, as it is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied in the eternal being, who is your eſſence, if ye are riſen, and ſo an unione in one.</p>
            <p>Brethren, let me ſpeak unto you; the Lord ſwore unto me, ſaying, <hi>Theaurau-John my ſervant, I have choſen thee my ſhepherd.</hi> Now time will ſpeedily manifeſt whoſe I am. Brethren, this I know, that all the whole Scripture I ſhall abſtract into a ſhort ſcope, and then the abſtract of that, with that that God will declare and manifeſt by ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, for God will confirm the teſtimony of his ſervant; but I am a childe as yet, but my ſtrength is daily increaſed, but I remember no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, for what I have given me, 'tis ſuddenly, in the word I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and no other ways.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>
                  <hi>Eltham</hi> the 25th of <hi>March.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord, demonſtrate thy ſelf in the beauty of excellency, that all may know thee, O Lord, for thou art a great, and glorious God, clothed with Majeſty. The Earth, the Heavens, the All, is but Thee; and thou O God art that All. From which All, all things came forth, and being here refined, they return, to their centred being, which art thou, O God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The prayer is but ſhort, but in this ſhort abſtract, lies imbodied, all that can be ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="letter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170906:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Epiſtle VIII.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat that you charged upon me to anſwer, what I had declared, and ſtand and ſay Gods gift is perfect; I beſecch you hear me, and minde my words: know, 'tis the glory of the meſſage, if admited the weaker the perſon is; for my not being able to diſpute the thing, 'tis my glory that I am taken into that thing, and loſt in my ſelf. Now if you would be judicious you might ſee cleerly, 'tis God all in me, I dead in the thing, to my coyned invention, and it ſelf demonſtrating it ſelf; becauſe man ſhall have no glory, but in being it ſelf mans all. So brethren, minde <hi>Pauls</hi> words; I am dead to live, not I, but he in me, ſurely you forget this text. Now beloved, here lies the great difference betwixt knowledge and lying learning: he that hath knowledge, his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is to keep cloſe his heart, that a motion ſtir not, to think a thought, but even to be dead clay, before God; The learned labours, to know names, and words of excellency of expreſſion to pleaſe men, for his own credit and repute; but brethren, I tell you, that now ſince I ſpake to you laſt, I know no man ſhall be able to ſtand before me in knowledge, although I am thus weak at this day.</p>
            <p>Beloved, <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation, ſaw the variety in the unione, from whence comes unto us this letting down, <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the end, and the beginning.</hi> Now to render the reaſon, to your capacity, why I hold not the word, as the original holds it forth, the reaſon is; my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>John</hi> was a beginning, flowing forth in that makka demikal expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I come to put an end to that makkademikal expreſſion; therefore as he ſaid, <hi>I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end.</hi> Now I <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aurau-John</hi> ſay, <hi>Omega &amp; Alpha, &amp; elouſtrationes, heck duo noſe in vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſummum, in abſtrackcie in reamus ol ſene ſebat allah-en;</hi> The deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey, the end to man is better then the beginning, for the beginning is trouble, the end is reſt. So beloved, I ſay <hi>Omega &amp; Alpha,</hi> the end and beginning: I am to inter, or bury the falfe gloſs, put upon the true Scripture, in the grave of oblivion and darkneſs, and likewiſe to cauſe Chriſt to raign, in the true divine Evangelical expreſſings, which at this day lies murdered, by the greekiſh compoſive, in the new-Teſtament, ſo called. <hi>O aloe ſenat annai ſele rem.</hi> O the hidden truth ſhall have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170906:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>luſtrative, Evangelical expreſſion. <hi>Id via in reamus ſalma onch hal ab oli penan reaſana alphi ſele.</hi> O the divine truth ſhall have a peaceful glorious reſurrection, raigning over the Kings of the Earth, in full tranſcendency; O the riches of God ſhall be letten down to men, to attract their beatious ſouls, to the beautified builded, and center, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, in it ſelf, which is, God himſelf; now the pearls that the ſoul of of man luſts after, ſhall be letten down, even to the injoyment of it; and the ſoul ſhall imbrace its delight, in the eternal being, which is God. This is the everlaſting Goſpel that ſhould be preached, which is God dwelling with men, by a divine Evangelical living in them, they in it, here lies the myſtery; <hi>Theos eſt Deus in cor alla ſapuit ad amalam in re.</hi> The derivacy; God is God, when he rules in the heart, in the heighth, here is a Negative read from an Affirmative ſtate. The heart lives in God, when God lives wholly in the heart: Now here is the myſtery. Thus God lives in us, he cannot live out of us, 'tis ſo ſtated, therefore tis true, becauſe 'tis declared by God himſelf; but man lives not in God till God live wholly high in the heart of man; here lies the riddle of this expreſſion, God is good, and all is God, minde when the heart of man doth live wholly high in God, then the ſaying is true, but when God doth live in man, without man living in God, then the ſtate is falſe. Further thus, God lives in us by property in creation, thus his eſſence is our life, now know he cannot live our of us, except he live out of his own eſſence; which can never be now you will ſay that God lives not in wicked men, but I <hi>Theaurau-John</hi> ſay and know that God lives in wicked men, thus, God is the life of all; and every appearing thing is but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative outwardly, of that inward eſſence which is God living in us, as we are deſcended from the eſſence of God, which is our life in life; minde that ſtate ſtated. Now for God to live in all things, if duly conſidered, 'tis not ſtrange, for 'tis truth, and truth is not ſtrange, for things not true is ſtrange, for that is a ſtranger, that hath no center or dwelling, and that a lye hath not; for it is nothing: and nothing can have no center.</p>
            <p>Now then God living in us, by our blinde rule it follows, that then we muſt live in God, no it follows contrary, ſo that our rule is falſe, that we have meaſured our certainty by, for in that ſtate your negative will not hold the affirmative to center in; thus I beſeech you minde, the point is great, God is good undenyably by any, but for all his creation to be good in themſelves, that is denyed, Thus, the eſſence creative in us is good, for 'tis Gods image, but our diſcenting from that living life in us, cauſes the evil in us, and for want of ſight of that good eſſence, cauſes our detraction to go a whoring after other Gods, then we are looſened from the Tye within us, yet ſtill the eſſence of God is in us, but by the detracting acts, we declare, that we are not in God; or as you ſay of God: for Chriſt ſaith you are of the devil your Father, for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170906:23"/>he was a murther from the beginning, how was that? he was darkneſs and light, neither darkneſs nor light, what then? he was the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of light, and his ſtength was to unbaſe the light, or unfoundation the light, to erect his own foundation which is darkneſs, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of the one, is the extirpation of the other, that is, murthering one another. Now know that the light is God, darkneſs is ſuffered by God, which lyes in theſe two great declaratives, of day and night; for the day is, the night is not, the night is, and the day is not, this is to us, but to him that is both night and day, all is but one; for light and darkneſs is both one unto the Lord. Theſe two hieroglyphicks of day and night, were they but looked upon with enlightned eyes, they hold all in them, and do fully repreſent all things, and contain under their hieroglyphicie whatſoever is and is not, for 'tis time; O noble time! O glorious time! this time is our time of our glory, but though we are contained in time, in time we are looſened from time, ſo time is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us, we nothing to that: we are two in our diſtincts, both one in God, for to him all things is but one, but God living in us, is manifeſt, but our living in God is; <hi>Aufnah allah non,</hi> That is not deſcernable in any height, as the declaratives of <hi>England</hi> do manifeſtly declare, for we have a name of the thing, but 'tis a bare name, without the thing.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Loadicca,</hi> truly <hi>Englands</hi> true Emblem, neither hot, nor cold, but lukewarm; therefore is thy judgement coming, like a ſmoaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, that will overwhelm thee with violence: O the time of thy peace is paſt, deſtruction begins to enter thy Orbe, or habitations, for thou labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to bare rule and ſway by violence, that is not the Goſpels rule, but 'tis a falſe rule of thy own making, making a noyſe of acting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in name, but the truth in the root is another thing. God looks not at thy outſide paintings, but ſees thy ſecrets, and thy ſecret actings, yet know, that God lives in thee, but thou liveſt not in God: Thus, God lives in thee as thou art eſſenced in him, but thy living in him is not found in thee: This is a ſtrange ſtate, but to open it, it will appear too true, to thy ſorrow, and unexpreſſable ſufferings that are to come. Thus, minde, I prove, though God lives in thee, thou liveſt not in him, for thou liveſt in thy ſelf, for actions is the true declarative of living; the reaſon is, the action is more ponderous or weighty, then the word, and is a viſible declarative to men, what is in the heart, for the living in God, muſt be declared from the heart obedience, to be declared in acts of love, mercy, compaſſion, long-ſuffering patience, this is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative of God living in thee, nay thy living in God then is truth, when the negative comes to be read from an affirmative ſtate; that is thus, when thy will is unwilled, and willed again in obedience to act righteoſneſs, then thou art in God, and God in thee, and both in one. This was ſpoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was in his updraft, the life that I now live, is in the Son of God, and 'tis not I, but he in me,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170906:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>I in him; Here was before an affirmative, and a negative, then by acts ſecondly two negatives, thirdly both affirmatives, fourthly one acting diſtributive, which is mercy, mercy is God; and man drawn into that center, is made one ſpirit, ſo an unione betwixt God and man: I ſpeak your term to let you underſtand: but men is not man, but I paſs. Now you will ſay that man hath free-will, and again man hath not free-will, here is the main work, in the diſputing creation: Firſt, I ſay man had free-will in his firſt ſtate, now you are pleaſed, then I ſay that man hath not free-will in his ſecond State, now you are pleaſed: But to define what is meant in this myſtery; The Spirit of God is the true eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of both, Firſt man was man, which in his proper eſſencial center is perfect God, we in him did act his will, becauſe we in that will were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, in what act ſoever he acted, we in it, all our all was in him: Now minde, we by and in that will iſſued forth, ſtill the will was free; but minde that ſtate held not long after we were created, For Angels will was ſtrength, and that ſtrength, and the motion by that ſtrength, cauſed the fall, from the freedom of will; then out of this fall came we, that we call men, which declarative of number, is a declarative of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being in count with us, for ſtrength is when the numbers are drawn into one, that one is God, the centred centred Center. But to come to term or name <hi>Addam,</hi> that is as you conceive, as we are, but you ſay he was perfect, that point will not be convenient in that ſtate to ſpeak to, nor at that this time. Thus the will in <hi>Addam</hi> was free, though he was in fleſh; but thus, the motion of that will was tied upon the principle of obedience: now obedience denied free-will buried, but not loſt, for from that graue, in which the ſtem lies buried, the celeſtial ſtrength cauſes a reſurrection to obedience, and then free-will is produced out of that grave, that held the free-will in captivity; then your will is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, becauſe in obedience, and obedience is free-will, and no other thing. Now men hath not free-will, by reaſon of weakneſs, tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under that term, men, but when you come to be proper man, then free-will is your proper ſtrength, to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t in righteouſneſs, for Chriſt is the freedom of will, nay your obedience will. Now as man had in his firſt ſtrength free-will, ſo in Chriſt reſtored, man hath his freedom of will, renued to his firſt original Principle, that is in God, by obedience in Chriſt, that is, our freedom in him, for we are bound in our ſelves, and free in him, for if the Son have made you free, then ſhall ye be free indeed: <hi>Glavo oſana olla ſabinai el ono ophrates elma ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionalem ad me amalet ter ſeke on ſaddi audit petro ogamus ſola rem ſadit al,</hi> The glory of excellency of the creature, lives in free obedience of will, to will its will in obedience to his will, that gave it a being in light, of his own free will, <hi>O ſelos ſapuit in rem moum rationalom cudit erko on ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le rem.</hi> O the heavenly wiſdom! is divine obedience in the thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by wiſdom required, by wiſdOm obeyed, then Chriſt in us, we in him, both in God.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170906:24"/>
            <p> But the opinion of many is, I may cut my own throat, or deſtroy my ſelf, and ſay they, is not this free-will, and an act of my own? To both which ſtates, I anſwer, it is thy ſelf, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> acts declare it to be onely thy ſelf, but not in free-will, for thou miſtakes free-will grows on this foundation, that is, Chriſt freeing us from bondage of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt conceived free-will, planting us in him, he in us, then is man in free-will, but before in bondage to his own luſt, which he through the blindneſs of his deceived imagination, appropriates to himſelf free-will, when in truth tis bounden bondage in himſelf, in which every na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man lyeth buried. Another objection is this, from the ſame blinde principle: I can eat, drink, walk, do this, or let it alone. Now know, that in them actings is not freedom, for know they are centred in thy ſelf, and thy life bound in darkneſs, that thou ſeeſt not thy free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; therefore thy acts muſt, and are bound up in thy thick dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and as the <hi>Primum mobile</hi> is, ſo is the iſſuing declaratives all in bondage, for Chriſts freedom is perfect freedom, both in body and ſpirit, and declared by outward acts of mercy, pity, and compaſſion, and thou art unmerciful to thy ſelf, and by thy increaſing darkneſs, thou laboureſt to extinguiſh the light that ſhould unpriſon thee, and ſo thou becomeſt a fighter againſt thy God. Now you will ſay how can men be fighters againſt God? Now know you muſt underſtand, when I ſpeak men, you account man, and when I ſpeak man, you take it to be one man, when both the holy writ, and my ſpirit intend Chriſt the Saviour; alas till you come to theſe diſtinctions, you ſee not, for your heart is vailed: But beloved, I in the love I have to the gathering the Lords people, my brethren, I would become to be the ſoal for to let the loweſt tread upon, to raiſe him equal with the higheſt: <hi>Hoſo avallo onſo oli rebeah ſal,</hi> The divine light humbles men to the loweſt center, to give an equal riſing to all in the thing, that thing is God, but the tongues will not bear it in proper word, to hold truth in word and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure: <hi>O agoremus in ſabie ſenat allah phiei ſebat:</hi> Them two laſt words are the Greek words, to bring the meaning down from the original, to a compoſure of Olymet under the equinoctial; for do you know the word muſt be truth, in the word, in compoſure, and adjunct, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct, and in the very horizantal muſt bear equal witneſs with the word, elſe not truth, but this is Gods word, when tis writ in truth of word, in truth of place, in truth in time; theſe three make it truth, and it cannot be truly Gods word, if any forecited thing be wanting in the Engliſh derivacy of the forecited ſtate: O! the glory of the thing is, to have its obedience due unto it ſelf: <hi>O! allah in rem ſapuit allah ſanatar al:</hi> The heighth of obedience is, the glory of the tyed thing, to return to the free thing, that free thing is God, unto whom is obedience due, as he is the Creator. Now beloved brethren, to come to the explicatory point of points, which is this, God in man, man is in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170906:24"/>God: God cannot be properly out of any thing, for the all things make but his eſſence, which eſſence is truth, and taken up to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is God in perfection. Now then will you ſay that God is all: under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand but your own word, and then you will ſay as I ſay, for if he had not been your all, you had had no being: Now this is his eſſence all, which is a divine all: But I ſhall ſhew you another all, to you, but both alls, is but one in him; for there is a regency all, as well an eſſency all, and a regency eſſence as a regency all: Thus the regency eſſence is, when we are taken into it, it operateth in us all obedience, that is, the eſſence regency: Now the regency all, is this, when the regency eſſence is taken up into the regency all, then and not before to us, all is all, and then we are that all, from whence we came forth, but yet a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but of Angels, for then our all is his all, his all is our all, and together both one all.</p>
            <p>The expreſs of man and woman holds forth the true emblem of this ſaying, for the woman and man are but one fleſh, nay the woman and the man then are but one ſpirit; This hieroglyphicy of man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, holds forth more then can be fetched out with mens learning, but not ſuch matches as we make, for we in our blindneſs make a trade of matching; 'Tis matching indeed 'tis no more then buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one another: this is not the man and woman ſpoken of in unione, but tis of the Devil, and unlawful, whatſoever mans law ſaith to that and luſt ſaith to that, I ſay by the grace given unto me it is whoredom and adultery, and the time is at hand, that God will puniſh for theſe things: Mans laws cannot make Gods paths, but Gods paths ought to be the rule of mans laws, O <hi>England</hi> then! where is thy pretended holineſs? but know pretence is a lye, and not the thing: <hi>Vis in ſe in afflictionem in tran humanitas in ſal elomon:</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wilt ſee when affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is centered in thee, then is the time that my word will take place: Remember what I ſpeak this day, for the time of viſitation haſtens, <hi>O ſe, o ſe, o ſe,</hi> O thy ſelf! oh thy ſelf! oh thy ſelf! is thy own ruine, yet theſe words will not print in thy ſpirit, but when afflictions have made naked thy vains, then thy lancing is near, then the plaiſter will be ſeaſonable, but not before, then a word will enter, when affliction hath made the way, thou art too high to hear, I was too high to ſpeak, but know I am thy true emblem, but mine is in mercy for thy at laſt healing, I know what I ſpeak: O I dare not pray for thee, becauſe I know thy puniſhment is ſealed, and the ſentence is gone forth: <hi>O amorum</hi> is turned to <hi>bellum,</hi> that is, O thy lovelineſs is war, which is weakneſs: O how hath our religious ones purchaſed to themſelves by blood, The foundation ſhall not ſtand: <hi>O afuah al ſene am ardine aam ſab oli open ſera vertet al:</hi> O the perverſneſs of men, ſlaying one another for nought, nay nothing, for the glory of a name of dung, <hi>o ſo agaous ſal bene neck ſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſere mem:</hi> The nothing which is dung, ſlays the nothing for dung,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170906:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>which is not perfection, but weakneſs: O that you were, that you ſay you are, then would mercy flow forth as a riſing Sun, but ye are not that you ſay you are, your actions are true declaratives of what you are, for they are of greater weight then your words. But to come to the divine Myſtery, which is God himſelf in himſelf, and all times, in one time, and that time is God. Now beloved, ſomething is let dwon to lighten you, concerning the promiſes promiſed to the ancient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Jews, my brethren according to the fleſh. Beloved, do but reade the Bible, and minde how the ſcope of ſcripture doth coatrefie one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to inſert the entire certainty of the Jews return from whence the Lord hath ſcattered them: O <hi>England</hi> thou <hi>Akeldama</hi> to that people! O! thou haſt murthered without mercy, know that root ſhall unroot thee, for thy judgement haſtens, and thy ſin is brought in remembrance before the Lord. Beloved, we many of us pray for the converſion of the Jews, do you declare from the heart the thing you utter. Now know, I am Jew of the tribe of <hi>Ruben</hi> begotten by the goſpel, which is Maſſah, El, Jah, or Jehovah, Jeſus, or Chriſt, all theſe are but names of that one merciful thing, that is God. Now beloved, all you that have pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the converſion of the Jews, ought to return praiſe to God that one is converted to the goſpel, and thouſands by that one, ſhall be brought forth in time, and ye Gentiles ſhall rejoyce with his people, tis <hi>Pauls</hi> own words, ſaying, Rejoyce ye Gentiles with his people: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw this time, by the ſpirit that is produced by us: for ye ſhall all be taught of God, that teaching is turning all Jews: Minde them words, for tis not one outwardly, but he that was one inwardly, that is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual one. Now <hi>Paul</hi> was a Jew, both outwardly and inwardly, as I by the grace given unto me am. He of the tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> I of the tribe of <hi>Ruben.</hi> Now know God who is all, can take and chuſe, and change when he pleaſes, and where he pleaſes, and no change in him from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but in us is his changing; the Prieſt-hood in <hi>Levi,</hi> the Prieſt-hood is now in <hi>Ruben,</hi> for the gathering all the whole Tribes, and Gentiles into one root, that is Maſſah, El, Jah, or Jehovah: <hi>O arorum in ſabie el ſede cleckci per quod non hock ackki el ſele orata in ſe meam operati el pekod oli in rem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſaying of the holy Ghoſt (termed by you Gentiles) is but the ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ſame ſpirit in the prophecy of the Prophets; for that that you call the holy Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or the holy Spirit, it is but the ſame, the truth of God in the meſſenger, or Prophet ſpeaking forth the received light, to elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate into the underſtanding, to cauſe a reſurrection unto obedience. Now the words that are rendred in the New Teſtament, is thus deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, Try the ſpirits whether it be of God, or no: theſe very words are falſe tranſlated from the Original, to hold up lying learning. The word in truth of words is, <hi>Penan al ſede mem dene en ſane,</hi> The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, The ſpirit of God tryeth all things. Now I ſhall appeal to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170906:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>judgement, to weigh theſe two Texts: Firſt conſider, man naturally is blinde, for the natural man perceiveth not the things of God, for they are ſpiritually deſcerned; then how can the Expoſitor bend his expoſition, for the word ſtated holds all times, and ages, and people, for tis an admonition to blinde people without eyes, which is thus much, I know a man ſtone blinde, and I bid him judge of colours: Weigh it well the Maxime will hold, <hi>in veras veritatas.</hi> Now to the ſpiritual man, tis his ſight, it is as much as to ſay, ſee your own eye, when the eye is its own ſight. So do but conſider judiciouſly, you will begin to be ſick of your learned lying believing, and a hundred more of the like conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is ſtated to hold up the Prieſts trade, but now the light will unbottom all that have bottomed themſelves, or their ſelf ends, which is the teaching of God in a tranſcendant manner: <hi>Ezeche el ſele mem deos in ſe penan ori oramus in ſe ſalma apanar ſele mem:</hi> The derivacy in Engliſh, The divine teaching is the ſpirit inſpiring knowledge into the underſtanding of man, which teaching is unavoydable true, for it levels all before it, and erects its own center in deſpite of oppoſition: this is Gods teaching. We do but name the thing, from the experience we have in thing, but God himſelf doth inlet the thing, for it doth require no leſs ſtrength then his own omnipotency. Now know, I am in my way as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, for the Jews was read to: Our words ſtand ſtated, and cannot be turned by the airy notion of an empty ſpirit, to make they know not what. What I have laid down, let all look upon that pleaſe, this ſhall ſtand, I have the Lords Seal to confirm my teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: <hi>Sele mem, ſele mem, ſele mem,</hi> This is the heavenly perfection in truth: <hi>Humanitans in cor ſelorum in reamus mem,</hi> Theſe are the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings down to mortals, to draw their minds to perfection, which is in God, <hi>O ormoas in ſelem ſabie el deorum, ſapuit dolma apanitorium ſelum:</hi> O the lovely evangelical dwelling, is in the peaceful dwelling, which is in the paradaical eſſence, which is God himſelf, and our ſafe Center. O beloved! if your ſouls were but touched with that elixer, or that evangelical Light, O it would be ſo great an atrackt, that your eye would ſo dwell upon that: All below that would be donge unto you, but ye dwell in your ſelves, and your own life is your rule, for you are ruled by baſe corruptable things: <hi>O skubulo orkas,</hi> the donge of donge. O beloved! do not dwell upon that, that is not, ſtand and look and expect the light of ſalvation from the Lord: Not that I can ſay do this or that, for know that doctrine leſſens the merciful mercy; as thus, if any thing in me, then 'tis a help for me, but nothing in me, then hee's my free all: <hi>Allah aſanal oli dene mem,</hi> He is the heighth in reſtoring the hidden thing: <hi>O avan aſzi ſele al ogoas ſabdi an ſelorum,</hi> O the contrary doctrine laboureth to deceive the thing, but the eſſence Tye, holds the tied thing unto the high all, and at laſt brings it to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly reſt: <hi>O in ſanctum ſanctorum metrobilorum in a naſah al oli dele
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170906:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>mem,</hi> The holy of holieſt is the receiver of the divine thing, into it felf, unto which place bring us, O God, through Chriſt thy mercy.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſtle IX.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GOd who is the true Elixer, and that Atrackt of beauty, that atra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teth, by his beauteouſneſs, all things, to a ſtand, or maze, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that ſtanding maze, their beholding his glory of excellency, in a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt are turned into himſelf, the fountain, yet reſt to all, for the tranſcendency of his excellency is over all, and that all is all things, and yet that all, is not comprehended in any one thing, or all things, for 'tis himſelf comprehending himſelf, and all things are but ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viant unto him, that is, their all without them, yet they not without him. This is Jehovah his name, and to it obedience is made the ſame in love. Beloved, God in his foreknowledge ſaw the creature would detract, by reaſon of the ſtrength of motion in the will, for the ſtrength of motion was the fall. Now the free-will in God, cauſed the creation, ſo the free-will in God is our reſtoration by Chriſt, which is but the mercy of God, letten down to take his created into himſelf: <hi>Hos ſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſolma anni dede mem:</hi> The letting down the creation was a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of Gods excellency: <hi>In evan ſam ſene allah en ſele mem,</hi> The ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the life created into him, is the bringing his wearied creative into perfection in himſelf: <hi>O avallo eternitas in ſem ſadei mel tedet alli ne pekod ol on,</hi> The point of election is not in any original, but for want of the true underſtanding, the true intent of the ſpirit in that place of the Romans, concerning election and reprobation. Now brethren I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you by the mercy received, if not my words are in vain, for 'tis that mercy that giveth you eyes to ſee mercy, even but it ſelf, in a higher illſtration, for the truth of mercy, is as true in the eſſence all, as tis in the regina, or reigning all, that is, when the eſſence is taken up into the regency, that is to ſay, God in himſelf, reigning in himſelf, that is, when the eſſence is taken into himſelf: Thus you are derivacy from and in that eſſence, you are a derivative, derived from that eſſencial eſſence. Now your tye, or life, is in the eſſence you came from. Now when you that are the derivative, are uneſſencied, that is, thus much when your ſoul is taken away (which is your eſſence) into the regency
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170906:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>all, then you ceaſe to be a derivative here, but you are a regency in that all, that you were but eſſenced too and from before.</p>
            <p>Brethren, you weak ones, I cannot let the ſtate down to you, but God will build you to it; for the ſpirit that I come forth in, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the Gyants in notional knowledge, or learning; for ſince man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited the Globe, was not there a greater ſhew of light, in name, but bring it to truths rule, then its center will not be found; for 'tis mans conceived thing, but 'tis not the true thing that is centred in God; but ayry vaniſhing lye. But now beloved, I <hi>Theaurau-John</hi> am ſent to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock the locked depths of mans darkneſs, and unvail the truth, that lies buryed in the Greekiſh compoſure, or the New-Teſtament ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, amongſt us Gentiles, but the true Jew, hath the true ſight, to make a clear diſcovery of the truth in that called Teſtament.</p>
            <p>Now to the point of points, the all points. That is ſtated in theſe words; Gods election from eternity of ſome, and Gods reprobation to eternity of others. O my God open your underſtanding, for this riddle ſhall be unridled before you all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aloe ſene mem deloos in ſabiet elma aparata al.</hi> Minde, the divine God, thinketh not mans thoughts, but in himſelf is free. I beſeech you minde that word <hi>free,</hi> for that word carrieth the whole import in the ſtate. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos al beneam addi en een ſelet alpht ſegat ar-ab in ſe.</hi> Neither doth God call man to an account, as we account it; for minde, Hels, or I Am. Now if the truth were but reached out of Is, or I Am, diſputes were at an end, but for want of the true knowledge in that ſhort ſtate, come the multiplicity of writing and diſputing without end. But beloved, now to come cloſe to the point; that is, firſt Gods eternal decree or election of ſome, or rejection of other ſom. Firſt, we will reaſon as Brethren, as men, then I will ſhow the cited word, from the truth, but no original that root hath to grow on, but 'tis a foyſted weed privately crept in, to leſſen nay deſtroy, the ſweet fragrancy of the true beautious delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble flowred flowers growing in Gods garden, which is the ſpiritual ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in the heart of man, then you ſhall ſee the coherent of the written word, called Scripture, both Old and New.</p>
            <p>But to begin to reaſon as men, Firſt know, that God Is, that is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, his acts are intire, One, always the ſame; now know, that if it ſhould be, as is declared, the very words would deſtroy God, and make him no God at all; For thus you make God partial, like man, which God doth condemn all along in Scripture, the words of God are, do juſt, without partiality, know Gods commands are like himſelf, nay they are himſelf; now minde, for God to take part of his eſſence, and deſtroy part, know you God cannot do it, for he Is, and cannot be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways. I beſeech you minde, Is, is the myſtery lies in that ſtate, though ſo ſhort yet you reach it not, though 'tis cleer as the light, but thus, for God to receive part of his eſſence, and caſt away the other, 'tis
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170906:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>as much, as I ſhould pluck out one of my eyes, and affirm I have two, and ſee with both, when all people that views me know the contrary. But one more, look to this contrariety, if God ſhould but act as you ſpeak, I declare before all the world, he could not be God, the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome ſay you is mercy to them, the rejection of ſome, is juſtice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>Now I <hi>Theaurau-John</hi> demand of you my Brethren, what was it that created and gave life to all things, as well as men and women, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what were they made of, you muſt all ſay that God, or the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, cauſed this produced creation, now I demand, what cauſed God to create, was it not his will alone; no, he hath no will, for he Is, and Is hath no will, for 'tis, and that Is, God, in his free all, where is no will; therefore, in the whole current of the Old and New-Teſtament, that word will is falſe, for Is, is the proper demonſtration of his excellency; yet Brethren again, God could not choſe, for it was himſelf eſſencying himſelf, in created appearances, what a madneſs below men, to think that God could choſe, when all was but himſelf, what could he chuſe, when all was to come forth of himſelf.</p>
            <p>I tell you there neither was, nor could be choſing, when all was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the womb of unione. One ſtep farther, thus, what a God would you make, if he could chuſe, or not chuſe; be pleaſed, or be angry; by this very doctrine you make him, that is all, one intire figure or ſimblim, of the weakeſt in all his royal royalty, in his whole creation, that is to ſay the weakeſt man, for a ſtrong man will ſcarſe be angry.</p>
            <p>But now to come to his refuſing or damning; that word is like a ſheperds dog to the ſheep: for to fright the ſheep to the fold.</p>
            <p>Brethren that word from his fatal habitation, rayſed <hi>Apollyon,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baddon;</hi> that is, the greekiſh Faulkon, to fly home to their preying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is thus much, the prieſt holds you in aw, with a devil, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, &amp; while you are all your days pondering upon that torment, they in plain terms pick your pocket; for that was the great noiſe that hath deceived the people, and brought them in miſerable bondage in ſpirit, and perpetually inbondaged them to the Clergy tiranny. O if no Tythes, then ſhake <hi>Abadons</hi> chains, then make the all people tremble. But now to come to the original word, from whence this cheat came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Notions. <hi>Patroas in ſol ori in ſaba al opiei pelma abadit el ſeke avaron,</hi> The ancienteſt Fathers ſaw a Sun, in which this cheat had no center.</p>
            <p>Now minde, nothing can have a being, but from and in God; now this lye of darkneſs, hath no being in light; for 'tis nothing but a meer cheat, of the Romiſh Clergy, to hold up themſelves, and the Popes ſupremacy.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the originaleſt of things, Then Prieſts your eſſence, which is the Greek tonge, or lying tonge; you muſt ſearch you a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170906:27"/>which muſt come at laſt to take Sanctuary: the truth that is vail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Greek tongue, muſt come to be radified in the Hebrew Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet; there I ſhall eſpy your ſhifting cheats.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the word from whence this Amazonian whore takes unto her her regency, the fatal derivacy, this was the whore that <hi>John</hi> ſaw, that the peoqle committed fornication withal, 'tis the greekiſh compoſure of lies, to intangle men withal, with her whoriſh-forehead; look in <hi>England,</hi> is ſhe not dyed in skarlet, is not religion the colour for us to act all our vilany under, if not a notion New-Teſtament man, then there is no marching in our whoriſh train, for we are gone a whoring aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other Gops, for that God I know is love, mercy, goodneſs, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is not found amongſt men, that cry up a name, to effect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing.</p>
            <p>But for theſe dubious words, from the Hebrew I finde none, no neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the devil, or hell, or damnation, then <hi>Thou</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The derivacy in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> is Gods truth, thats hell to darkneſs; now you Scholars will ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſin,</hi> now to you great Magies, I ſay, and you muſt ſay, that the true originality of the pronunciation is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'tis your pointing her on her left peat, that make you read her <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſin</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> know you read her <hi>ſhin, ſiin, ſin,</hi> but Brethren, ye Prieſts, I know thirty ſeaven diſtincts, beſides your three in that character, when you know ſo far of that Character, you are no neerer finding me, then light to darkneſs, for then I can make the knowledge of that Character, run in motion, in the Celeſtial influences, and deliver that Character, into the center from whence ſhe iſſued forth, that is in God himſelf, you know not what <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhinn</hi> is, I will give you a denomination of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhinn,</hi> ſhinn is proper, not without two <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> her ſignificant in her origini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, is the impeader of <hi>Sambah</hi> or <hi>Sam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhe is ſhinar in the clue, in the fraternity of the Planitor an Sheem; Beloved I intreat your patience, while I repeat theſe high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratives of Gods wiſdom, ſhowen me, not of me, but it ſelf expreſſing it ſelf, through this vail of fleſh, theſe are let down to confound the wiſe worldly men, to unbottom them, that God may lay the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhin</hi> the Engliſh is a declarative of beauty, or the illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of cleerneſs, though <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhinar</hi> be an impead to Sambah, that is the ſtrong king <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Plannets, yet the impead of his ſtrength, is by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Shiner, but from that impead of Sambah, his ſtrength <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Shinns</hi> cleerneſs, or beauty, beautifies Sambahs ſtrength, ſo in them two Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, is beauty and ſtrength, ſtrength and beauty that product is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, in the terreſtial orbs, by the ſpecies of their influences. So much for <hi>ſhin</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>thau,</hi> them are the Hebrew radicals.</p>
            <p>Now if I come to the greek, the original and firſt word coherent in his tongue, holding in weight with the Hebrew, it is <hi>Othroas,</hi> the exact ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant in Engliſh, is thus much, a departing, a detraction, a diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170906:28"/>anihilating, or a falling away, this is neither devil nor damnation; ſo much for <hi>Othroas.</hi> Then one word more, a greek word it is, <hi>Penan,</hi> now the ancient expoſitors have laid more upon this word <hi>Penan</hi> then it can bare, for they have ſtated an irrecoverable ſtate upon it (as we tearm it) thus much damned, that as we in our unruddered Engliſh runs, loſt for ever, which the word will not bare, for to hold truth in word, it is but the very ſame with <hi>Othroas,</hi> that is a diviſion, or ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or diminution, or leſſening. But to come neer your lying original, this word <hi>Euſei eel,</hi> that is the greek wrote from the hebrairak <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof in mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hes,</hi> that you underſtand not <hi>Euſei eel,</hi> now <hi>Euſei</hi> in your expreſſion is leſſening, add but <hi>eel</hi> to <hi>Euſei,</hi> then <hi>eel,</hi> makes and takes into it ſelf, what <hi>Euſei</hi> had leſſened and detracted, that is thus much; <hi>in ſe operat al aſabi el dele mem.</hi> The detracting detraction is taken into him, that is perfection, that is in plain tearms man taken into Ged, and then is perfection to man.</p>
            <p>Now I come from the place of torment in the words, I ſearch the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the place, what is he, 'tis rendred in the greek <hi>Abadon,</hi> or <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyon,</hi> now what is the weight of theſe words, in their import; Brethren, I would not deceive you, nor know I cannot deceive you, and yet I ſhall deceive your ſuppoſed truth, thus, if I demonſtrate the light, and pull down your builded darkneſs, then my light deceives your darkneſs, and being thereby deceived, in your own foundation, we are made both one in light, then your loſs is gain. But to come to <hi>Apollyon,</hi> or <hi>Abadon,</hi> theſe two names are rendred for one very ſuppoſed thing, now the true import of the words will hold thus much, a deceiver, or (I will give this, that you have attracted an accuſer, now to ſhow what this deceiver, or accuſer is, this is the myſtery. The deceiver is in man, that is, the dark ſpirit in man, that <hi>Paul</hi> tearmeth to be enmity againſt God, that is the deceiver, the accuſer, nay I give your own tranſlation (though it will not bare it) the accuſer of our brethren, what is this, he that doth deceive the very ſame doth accuſe, that is ſtill the dark ſpirit of unbelief in man, that is the called devil, that muſt be caſt forth into ntter darkneſs where, and when, when the ſpirit of light is taken into the center of light, which is in God himſelf, the body Evangelical, into the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daical living, the evil ſpirit or luſt, or deceiver, or deſtrover into dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in the grave, or hell, for the grave, is denominated hell, or the grave. Now the papal faction, hath made this fine cheating definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Ouſe ſe antimon ante tere elomon in ſe evan Haluleiah in ſe bene n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l pethrat alli evan aſareth ſephi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Hegemonians</hi> or Papiſts do declare, that there is three ſtates, for the refining the ſoul of man. The firſt is here by penance. Secondly, In Purgatory by indulgence. Thirdly, in the boſom of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which is reſt after refinement,</p>
            <p>This opinion is not new, for Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the firſt, was the inventer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170906:28"/>of this exhauſting ſum of ſums, into the Clergies tuition, for you being not perfect, hereby Penance may have your indulgence, or remiſſion out of Purgatory for mony, and ſo by conſequence the kingdom of heaven is earned by Prayers, or purchaſed by mony, forgetting the word of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> their main piller, that when mony was offered to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe the holy Spirit, by the Sorcerer <hi>Simon Magus, Thy mony periſh with thee,</hi> ſo ſay I, thy Prayers, that are founded on that foundation, to purchaſe, or payfor Gods free mercy, they periſh and come to nothing.</p>
            <p>But beloved, know there is nothing loſt, but all that is come forth is refined, acting his end he came for, and returns to his center, Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved know, that the New-Teſtament we have at the third hand, for the originality is in the Bible, and muſt hold coherent in unione with the truth there, for 'tis but an illuſtrative by the Spirit of that unione maxim, now to come to the Bible, there is truth and the lye in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, but that came through innocent ignorance, in not knowing the weight, or import of the originality, of the various maxims, that are herogliphically typed out in the Hebrew radiaſes, for one radax by the litteral man, is taken for another; for onely the ſpirit that is light, doth demonſtrate the truth from his own lettings down, which learned man cannot reach.</p>
            <p>Now to cite the radaxes, where the firſt error took denomination; the firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>phe,</hi> for ſhe is read in many places for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being both much like our Engliſh great C ſtanding with her points backward in the Engliſh Alphabet, the one is in the interpretation, an impead or hinderance, and and the other is the great influ of all the radaxes, for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>phe,</hi> ſhe is the cleerneſs of obſcurity, or the tranſcendency of beauty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n her ſtate, now ſhe is in her ſelf radical, 3, 4, 5. ſhe is the golden number, thus cleerneſs comes from her root; for ſhe is bottomed on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhinn,</hi> for that ſtate but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: before Shinn, and then the ſtate will bare perfection, for they are both one; now to know by ſtating a Character, by another, the myſtery is to know the weight of both together, ſeveral by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeves, in any place of adjunct: or conjunct, in eſſency, and derivacy, and in examinacy, and in definacy, and admonicy, in admittancy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junckſie and diſjunckſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but to come from theſe high ſphears, and to begin to plow in this terreſtrial field. I <hi>Theaurau-John-Eval-alſi-al allah al,</hi> do declare this day before all you people, and deſire you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare from me this day, That though Election, and Reprobation be ſtated in the New-Teſtament ſo called, it is abſolute blaſphemy, and I in my maſters Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſty, do challenge the whole world to anſwer, and cleer the ſtated lye, for it hath no originality, and 'tis fathered upon <hi>Paul,</hi> which is a fained fiction, and he that ended the Revelation of <hi>John</hi> the Expoſitor to lay a curſe upon him that addeth, or diminiſheth, 'tis falſe, and no original <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oundation, but to binde men in an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient fear, to bring them in, and keep them ſubject to the Popes ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170906:29"/>Brethren though you do idolize that, that hath ſet the world on fire, it is but a bead Idol, compoſed to hold men in obedience, to time, and ſtate, This I ſhall ſhortly declare, for the life of all things is Chriſt the Lord, which is the mercy of God taking us into it ſelf, that is the <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> the chief all, or the chief good, but 'tis not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in that ſtate as the chief all.</p>
            <p>Now Brethren, your Bible and New-Teſtament, their originality is truth, for 'tis Gods declarative, but for you to conceive the Book, called Old and New-Teſtament, to be true, that is falſe; for know, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent to us, is from the Romiſh fingering, interweaving, and painting in, their traduced opinion, now we have that, they have added to, for there is an addition, but no diminution, but making multitudes of rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, to keep the peoples brains from idleneſs, to keep all inſlaved unto themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now Brethren let me ſpeak plainly to you, what have they, or you to do with the writings of the Apoſtles, why truly nothing at all, for they were that thing that you have gotten the bare name of it, this was ſuch a ones words, what is that to thee, except his Spirit that is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of theſe lettered names, be in thee, then thou art it, it thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art but a lyer, and thou art a thief, for thou lookeſt to come in by the name, which is not the thing, neither the true way, for the truth of <hi>Pauls</hi> words, are the ſpirit ſeated in thee, and thou by that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit art made to act outward obedience, from that inlightned, and renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed principle, which is centered within thee, from whence flows acts of mercy, relief, and pitty, and compaſſion, nay thou comeſt to be one acting diſtributive, then <hi>Pauls</hi> words are thy words, nay <hi>Paul</hi> is thee, thou art <hi>Paul,</hi> for light is but one ſpirit; <hi>O agomeon in ſe alphy ſele rem.</hi> O the hidden thing, when light is centered will ſhow it ſelf, <hi>elohim ackki el ſelos in re affermater in rebeah ſal oli penan arri afaniel.</hi> The Engliſh. The God of ſtrength doth cauſe a reſurrection from death to life, by his own quickning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Senat ori alſiel,</hi> The living God doth give life to all. Now Brethren, concerning hell, and the devil, as you take them words, in their center there is none, as the Lord lives, for hell and torment is, when the light begins to appear, and caſteth forth darkneſs, into utter darkneſs. But to lay down ſome method to prove it, thus, I intreat your patience; Firſt know, that there is but one originality, out of whoſe product all things is produced, this you cannot deny, then God ſaid all was good, 'tis Gods own word, therefore true; but if you will make a devil, from whence had he his originy, you will ſay from God, well, then, ad Gods word the Creation is good, Gods word is himſelf; therefore true; now how, and what, and where was this devil, the firſt original that you know of, was in the ſtory of Creation, in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> do you underſtand what <hi>Geneſis</hi> doth import, 'tis thus much, the genuine underſtanding in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170906:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>the practick part, of <hi>Theos-ologi,</hi> now many of you are as neer in the name <hi>Geneſis; Geneſis</hi> is an Hebrew word, compounded of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, for 'tis wrote from the Hebraick <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in mophes,</hi> that is the tyed ſtrength, or combinings, combined into ſhort ſimblems or radiaſes, that in a ſhort ſcope all may be viewed, that was the Prophets Cabaleſterial inclue, and their methodical method, that was much upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>undati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hieroglyphicy, that is to ſay a ſhort map, to view the Land by, there in <hi>Geneſis</hi> according to their germine lighted light, in that age; for cleerer and higher diſcoveries are in me to come forth, for no leſs then the full opening, both Law and Goſpel, and ſhutting them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one intire truth, though now they lye jarring one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by reaſon of expoſitions made by men, but the thing is one, the truth in both one, that is truth; but not all in both, but in both falſe, through mans invention, which will be opened in the great day; that is but thus much, the illuſtration of Gods truth, that is the reſurrection from dead. <hi>Anni ſelorum in ſabeah el zedeck alphi eloſterationem induo in enim una &amp; reamus in ſe ſegoas ſal almenienna in tranſaluorum in rem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie pelma aurauret eloah al et el ſeke em.</hi> The Engliſh derivacy from this golden number, being the five oriental languages, the year of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the earthly man, that is Peace let down from God on high, but war and diſcord it ſhall beget, becauſe of its tranſcendency, at length the Lion and the Lamb by it ſhall be made one, no hurtful thing ſhall in my mountain be, for I the Lord will alone be King.</p>
            <p>But for the demonſtration of the Devil. In <hi>Geneſis</hi> 'tis ſaid, he was more ſubtile or wiſe, then the reſt of the beaſts, I intreat you minde but your own words, or you are the ſame beaſt that he was, for he was the quick life and motion in the beſtial body, which is but darkneſs, which is but a confuſed Chaos, before that light of the ſpirit of life riſe, and caſt down, and caſt forth, this Gyant of our own underſtanding, and God erect his center, in the cleer manifeſtation of his glorious excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and then and not before, you ſee your beaſtlike knowledge, by reaſon of the inward indowment, you are higher inlightned, and orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſed, otherwiſe then other beſtial bodies are, but all one dung, in the center of dung, that are you to the two own, but 'tis true; therefore by men ought to be owned.</p>
            <p>Now to know this ſubtile beaſt in the field, in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> was the luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſire that took hold within the woman, for what repreſentation ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever outwardly cannot attrackt the eye of the ſoul, unleſs it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruddered, or looſened from the tye of obedience within, for if obedience eye his principle, the devil that luſtful deceiver, deſirer, deſtroyer, cannot act, nor ſeduce us. Now there is a myſtery in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> concerning the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, you would have me keep unione, onely <hi>Eve,</hi> and ſhe the mother of us all, I ſhall adde but one hebraick ſentence, to hold my intent; though locked from you, and I will plead with your named <hi>Eve,</hi> but my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170906:30"/>is locked in this ſtate. <hi>Avil, ſeal, ſine, ſean;</hi> them four words will hold me true, though I diſcourſe with you in your ſained truth, thus ſay you: <hi>Eve</hi> was <hi>Addams</hi> wife, made of his rib, and that you know is crooked, the woman was ſtraight, and not crooked then, for Gods works are ſtraight and perfect works, the maxim will hold ſtraight; But to come to terms in knowledge, it would be Quered who wrote the book called <hi>Geneſis,</hi> or <hi>Theos-ologi,</hi> which word will hold the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of God, but now 'tis written, 'tis not Gods declarative, for to come home, Gods declarative cannot be written. Thus, God commands man to write, gives him what he ſhould write, ſtill this is not Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative, for we the living ſimblims or figures, we are Gods declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and that writing is but a dead name, of the living things, of the thing, that thing is God, the living life of all things.</p>
            <p>But to come to the woman in the called Garden, ſhe took an apple, and it was death, and it was death to them both, I beſeech you all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple minde this abominable aſperſion, caſt upon the great, true, holy, and righteous Jehovah, for God (ſaith your riddle) <hi>ſaw that it was not good for man to be alone,</hi> but ſaith the ſame riddle, <hi>Let us make man in our image,</hi> who was that was ſpoken to? Now fetch your Greek names, and then comes perſons, in one eſſencial eſſence, but I paſs from that point, that is too high for our Engliſh Scholars to deal with; but let's come to the woman, that God firſt ſaw it was not good for man to be alone, but he would make him a meet help to deſtroy both; I beſeech you mind in many places the tranſlator hath repreſented the glorious God Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to have leſs wiſdom then a weak man, nay a very lying Ideot, ye ſtand out for your tranſlated Baal, for the lying tranſlation; becauſe 'tis wrote ſo, therefore 'tis ſo, ſay you, But I <hi>Theaurau-John</hi> ſay, 'tis a lye, though writ ſo, I will prove it ſo, and all men living that ſtand in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ending it ſo.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you, judge judiciouſly, and doth the woman ſtand in your riddle a meet help for the man? certainly you underſtand not Gods word, for you will make God to be a lyer, or cheater, or decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but whatſoever you tearm him to be, leſs then truth, the all truth, you do indeavour to undignifie him, for he Is, that Is truth it ſelf, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther going backward by detraction, or coming forward by eloſteration, but he is. Now you may ſay, What is he? the higheſt expreſſion, if duly underſtood, and conſidered, the main that can be ſaid, he Is, and that is the all things in appearances, viſible, and inviſible, and yet not viſible, for the inlivening life of all things is not ſeen, that is the eſſencial being of God in that appearance, and the outſide appearance is moved from within the inmoſt ſpirit. But to come to this poor woman liking an apple, and it brought death ſaith your riddle, or Bible in that place of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> give me leave to treat with you, I ſay there was no Apples, neither Trees; I prove it to your own ſtate, for you ſay God made man perfect in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170906:30"/>the Garden, then know there cannot be a help in perfection, for that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys perfection; neither Apples nor fruit for meat, for do you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand but what perfection is, and it admits no help, no deſire, no luſt; now judge ye ſeriouſly of your own riddle, and when you are return'd from me, declare to your lying Miniſters, ſaying, That they are lyers in tongue, though the truth be in the heart, for they prate they know not what. I deſire but any or all would engage me, in any matter of Old or New-Teſtament; ſurely they have taught to a fair end, that they dare not maintain what they have ſpoken, otherwiſe they are content to live upon the prey of the people, and hold that, but this I know, I ſhall ſhorten their methods, and put an end to their Tythes, for people will nor, neither ſhall they be blinded any longer, to part with their labour for the telling of a lye by the Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Now you may ſay to me, You finde fault with them, and you teach the ſame: now I anſwer, I teach not, that you may all perceive, by my weakneſs in defending any ſtate, know if it were a compoſure of man by learning, then man could anſwer the objection, but know this day that God hath raiſed up unto you the Prophet that was promiſed in <hi>Mal.</hi> 7.5. but that is not in our inſert, but the coherence is one with <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2. but who may abide the day of his appearing? for he is like fullers ſope, a refiners fire, he ſhall even fine the ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> now I beſeech you minde, who is the ſpirits intent in me to drive at, but at the ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> and their work, which as the Lord lives I muſt effect; for which work ſince I ſaw and ſpoke to you, I have a ſtronger ſtrength added to my name, that is <hi>Eval alſiel.</hi> Scholars, when I ſound L, hebraick, you know what it meaneth.</p>
            <p>But to come to the woman and the myſtery, and the inticement ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> or the intire meaning; this is the ſpirits meaning, for this you ſay was wrote by <hi>Moſes,</hi> which I ſay was not; my Negation is as ſtrong as your Affirmation; nay ſtronger, for ſay you, <hi>Moſes</hi> entered not the Land, what is meant by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Land, in the true hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicy to hold qualification with its inherent diameter? Scholars, that word diameter, muſt in that ſtate be read backward, as well as forward; for as <hi>Geneſis</hi> is a denotat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on ſtammeringly of things below, ſo 'tis a point of compaſs in the ſpirits hand, to ſhew the celeſtial center, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which center is all things perfect; and from that center all, even it ſelf came forth; now it is perfect in its center, and imperfect in its demonſtration; for 'tis Gods weakneſs in his appearances, which taken up into its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency all, 'tis perfect.</p>
            <p>But go come to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the original of that word is <hi>Musſhah,</hi> that is a proper word in the hebrew, the derivacy to cauſe the compoſure of the word, is from the hebrew Alphabet wrote <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now Scholars, read <hi>Musſhah</hi> from them three radical radaxes, then you will ſee what <hi>Moſes</hi> is, and what the import of the word beareth in his originality, 'tis thus
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170906:31"/>much, a dark diſcovery of the truth in light, now <hi>Moſes</hi> tyes up leſs in his inclue then his true originality will bear. Well, you ſay he entred not into the Land, why? by reaſon of being impeded with darkneſs, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he braick wrote, and where God gives a name, if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be there he is impeded, and after him ſhall a diſcovery of a higher nature be manifeſted.</p>
            <p>The next that came was Jeſus a Saviour or a Redeemer, to raiſe the truth out of <hi>Moſes</hi> his darkneſs or dark diſcovery; but how comes Chriſt? that very C is his impede, that is the humanity that locked in the divinity, this will not ſerve, for all men are locked in fleſh, but the word Chriſt is derived into Engliſh from the Greek word Kriſtos; now the ancient Greek wrote it, that is the ſame with the hebraick <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, though not the Character, a derivacy in ſtrength, from the hebraick <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof,</hi> ſo the ſtrength of import was the ſame in the Greek, as Maſſah in the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, for they were but one; in one ſtrength, for the Greek is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood from a true derivacy from the hebrew, is as true as the he brew is, if it be held in meeter and method, which muſt be done by one ſpirit in both tongues, and all tongues, as I have laid down before. But to come to <hi>Moſes</hi> and that ſtory of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the woman firſt, I ſay <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote not <hi>Geneſis;</hi> thus, that book was wrote before <hi>Moſes</hi> time five thouſand years, and you write but five thouſand years and odde ſince the Creation; give me leave to put one queſtion to you: How long was it ſince there was a God? You will ſay ever, I ſay not: Ever ſtops in the center, but God Is, that Is all time, and all things, at once ever the ſame; in that ſtate ever will ſtand, but <hi>Enock</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> what wrote he? for he was higher then any; where is the hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicks he wrote in? where is that there was ſuch a man your riddle ſaith, and that man wrote more, then all the Old and New-Teſtaments, and we have none of them, where are they? the ancient Jewiſh root have them in the Eaſt Orcades, in the clue of the Moon, under <hi>Saturn,</hi> this ſtate is ſtrange to our Aſtronomers, but at length we ſhall ſee this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct produced.</p>
            <p>Now Moſes led the children of Iſrael from Egypt to Canaan, that I grant, but for him to write Geneſis, I deny, prove you that he did, and then I am ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>But to come to the verity of the myſtery inſerted, 'Tis this, Gods letting down his royal eſſence in appearances, which lies involved in theſe words, <hi>Theos-ologi,</hi> that is Gods light in his declared Creation; now that word is proper Geneſis, for now I come to propriety of ſpeech. Now, the woman cited in that riddle, and named <hi>Eve,</hi> do but minde the weakneſs of the combine, for that word lies open in the very originality of it to miſpriſion.</p>
            <p>Now to come to grapple with you in that citation, it is neceſſary that we ſtate the point, that cannot be evaded; from this rule I lay down, to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170906:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>demonſtrate forth from that you cannot deny: God created all things ſay you, No ſay I: there is one thing eſſencied, in all things that are. Minde the being of your termed things.</p>
            <p>Now you look that I muſt keep to the riddle or Scripture (as you tearm it) well I will, though I know but the Scripture, yet I know be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the inſert there inſerted, that is not, neither hath a foundation, though there inſerted and ſtated.</p>
            <p>Now the man ſay you, God made of the duſt of the earth, I paſs that for greater maxims ſake.</p>
            <p>But the woman, the poor woman deceived by the Apple, and her meetneſs of help was deſtruction to both.</p>
            <p>Weigh it well, and bring forth true judgement to determine in truth, but the help that is to patch up this lye withal, is this: God ſuffered it to be ſo, for mans greater glory; Now minde, could man have greater glory, then he had when he was included in the eſſence of God, in the raigning all, or eſſence regina, or raigning in God?</p>
            <p>Mind, what doth this produce? thus much: God was little before, and he would be greater now, that makes no God at all; elſe he would bring man to greater glory (in reverence to his Majeſty I ſpeak) that was to no glory at all; thus I prove if greater or leſs in the eſſence of God, no God at all.</p>
            <p>Farther thus, God cannot admit of more or leſs, then no God; I ſpeak in his Regency eſſence.</p>
            <p>But now I come to his declarative eſſence creating, to ſpeak to that, thus: that God that made all, is the all; of that all accounted things.</p>
            <p>Now man and woman are one figure, the chief in the terreſtrial field, the higheſt flower: Now for God to give it an help to overthrow it, to woe and miſery, and the help made by Gods word good, God how will this ſtand in the riddle ridled forth? God that is juſt, holy and good, for to give a help to deſtroy both, how could it ſtand with his eſſencial eſſence?</p>
            <p>But to come to the true originality of things, God did give a good help to man, now I prove the woman good and a meet help to the man, thus, the deſirable minde of man is to luſt, the woman taketh away that luſt that deſired, in that ſtate the woman was good, you men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men underſtand what I mean, but this will not hold in full with Gods word, for good by God, is always good, and at all times to eternity, no end of goodneſs if by God ſpoken, thus the woman is perfect good; for the woman is the ſhe, out of whom is produced the whole iſſue of the appearance in Creation, in that ſtate ſhe is good.</p>
            <p>But to come to tearm, the woman is weakneſs to ſtrength, and that is good, for it doth like a foyle ſet off the luſter of the diamantal perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, thus God could not declare his ſtrength, unleſs a weakneſs to work his ſtrength upon; thus if all ſtrength, no variety; and variety
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170906:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>is the declarative of uniones ſtrength, for 'tis the ſole for unione to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, (I may ſay) his foundation upon.</p>
            <p>But to come to this poor woman in fault, 'tis ſtated <hi>Hevah,</hi> or you ſay <hi>Eve,</hi> now to come to prove the woman a perfect help to the man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word; the woman there is taken for the increaſe of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſtrength, thus God out of unione that was and is ſtrength, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all things, ſo the woman that the ſpirit drives at, in that ſtate is <hi>Hevah,</hi> that is the bringing the weakneſſes in creation, to ſtrength in the end perfection; for what the woman, that is weakneſs did produce, is by the ſtrength of the Creator taken into perfection, that is ſtrength, that is the head of weakneſs, or the womans head; that is Chriſt or God.</p>
            <p>But to come to this poor ſimple woman, 'tis man, for man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man make both but one fleſh, ſo ſaith your Scripture; alas poor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man accounted the weaker ſex, when in truth the ſtrength of both was in one ſpirit; minde them words, they are your own tranſlation; for the woman is not without the man, neither the man without the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Lord; they two be one fleſh, and the ſpirit of Jeſus makes them two; and himſelf with the Creation but onely one, in the unione; minde that ſtretch in that drift of extent.</p>
            <p>Still the poor woman that is ſo hardly thought upon by ignorant man, 'tis himſelf without eyes, for there the woman is the weak figure of Chriſt in the time, in the humanity. <hi>Sala operal el &amp; al in ſe humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantibus in ſe oly dele mem.</hi> The light divine doth inlighten the dark light in man and woman, to ſee their originality from whence they came. <hi>Selos in ſe, ſcoli pekad addet on et on in ſe ſeparati aal in ſe perna aquitarian et eloſterationem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Divine All giveth eyes to ſee it ſelf, the ſoul in all things, and all things is but an elouſtration, from that radical root, which is the thing of things.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, if you could but ſee this rooted Root, of and from that radical root you deſcencially deſcended, into what you are, then you would not look at the woman as in that dark manifeſtation ſhe was looked upon, but the truth in looking is to ſee both one, in the unione.</p>
            <p>Now minde, to winde up all, <hi>Abrahamus et Sarahi, et in duo ſed una in rem: Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> were two in ſhow, but one in the All Thing, that is obedience in God, now the reaſon that the woman is outwardly the weaker figure or ſemblem, this is the reaſon, for ſhe is dubious in generation, that is to ſay the doubtful gender or geneos, that word is the ancient <hi>Calde</hi> ſignifying generation, in that ſtate ſtated, but the word will hold with other maxims, importance of multiplicity, or numbers; yet the radical root lives in the terminine qualification; but to take this aſperſe from this poor woman, this it is, as the Lord lives, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is the mans weakneſs, the woman in that ſtate is the Creation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170906:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſt in the fleſh that was ſubject to vanity, and periſh to outward appearances, but in that diſplace, they are placed in him in the eternal center, from whence they came forth; Now minde, God Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated all ſay you for his grory, no ſay I, his glory is the all created; for he could not be greater nor leſs, but ſtill and always the ſame; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member but the rule of perfection, and it doth not admit of degrees; but to ſhut up the ſum in a ſhort ſtate, it is in ſhort thus much, God in appearances, they in forms of Eſſency, are weaker then in regency: Now there is all writings, diſputations, all election, reprobation, all ſinning, all ſaving, all learning, all truth, all teaching; in that ſhort ſtate, the man the woman in the Garden, Paradice typified out, if duly weighed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſpirit that inditeth it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O agor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ns in ſalvorum in ſe operted ad amalum in ſambah alin phiei ſele mem.</hi> O the heighth of things in their center, is beautiful, but in their obſtruct is darkneſs, being from their centered center.</p>
            <p>The major of this Epiſtle was wrote at <hi>Eltham</hi> by me <hi>Theaurau-John Eval alſiel allah al ſabbah skribah Jael Tanniour</hi> the Jew.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April the</hi> 5th. 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="letter">
            <head>Epiſtle X.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>O ye Babes,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YE glorious figures of eternal Deity! Beloved, God hath letten the ſtate down this day to your capacity. Beloved, the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unione, in the tranſcendent excellency of the divine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hath declared unto nay in us, by his ſpirit, the divine knowledge which is himſelf, thus God from all eternity did create ſtates and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in Creation, though but one Creation; and no degrees unto himſelf for glory, or not glory; to him is but glory, nay one glory; for when as we ſay, to do well, 'tis all one to him; or when we do ill, 'tis the ſame, neither adding to him, nor diminiſhing from him, who is <hi>aſa oli pene mem delos in ſe ſalu in rem emanet al.</hi> The goodneſs in man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth no advantage to God, or the evilneſs in man hurteth him not; for know once come to be man, that is in propriety of ſpeech, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not act out of his will, as you call it, but God hath no will, for he Is, and Is hath no will.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170906:33"/>
            <p> Now to come to lay down unto you ſome methodical method, that that you may take from that ſome inſtruction, or inlighten your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>The Text is this, Love one another. <hi>O allu ſelos in rem Evangelies in ſe arri el.</hi> O the lovelineſs turns men into Angels with God himſelf in the Celeſtial center. <hi>O avaran in ſal moniam in re faciunter ad amalam.</hi> The Love in us ties us to one another in love, and being made in love, by that love, are taken into the heavenly center of eternal reſt. <hi>O a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum in ſe ſalvorum in re ſemper apellorum.</hi> O the lovelineſs in love, is the extract of beauty, from God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Beloved, That you could but ſee your ſelves to be your true ſelves, then lovelineſs is your royal ornament, in the excellenteſt tranſcendent magnificenteſt manner.</p>
            <p>O noble love, that unnobles the nobleſt Nobles, of their accounted nobility, and implants its nobleneſs in them, then are they truly nobled noble.</p>
            <p>Beloved, God did let down the nobility of his royal Creation in unione, that is in love, and how came thence detraction? it is for want of love in themſelves: Thus God loved us, that he gave his ſon Jeſus which is a Saviour, for to ſuffer for us, this was love. Now how this Saviour ſuffered, 'tis not underſtood.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God created all good, then the detraction, or falling away was the fall. Thus for God to have a detraction in him, it cannot be; for God cannot detract from himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, man detracted or fell, what was the reaſon? it was for wanting love; now I beſeech you minde, as man detracted for want of love, 'tis the ſame in you; for love ties the true-loves knot; for love there is no end of it, neither beginning; for 'tis God himſelf, in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Seloſe, in, re, ex, id, in, amalam, ar.</hi> Love is the heavenly and divine beautifyer of that, that was evil in it ſelf; thus thy envy, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and luſt, and every contrariety, if once love come to erect his throne, thou art turned into love; thy acts are in love, ſo far that from night, thou art turned into cleer day.</p>
            <p>O beloved, I can but ſpeak what I know of love; but I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to you: the naming it to you will not confer it to your precious ſouls.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, I ſhall ſpeak a ſtrange doctrine to what hath been taught unto you by your Miniſters; they ſay Do this, and do that good work; now miſtake me not, for in that good work, though good to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, yet 'tis not thy goodneſs, for know untill thou be crucified in thy ſelf, thy actions are dead, though never ſo great and good to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thus ſaith the Scripture, Be dead to live, how is that word meant? that word is a glorious truth in its originy, for he that ſpeaks it is the Lord; whoſe power is in that word, to cauſe a death unto thy luſtful
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170906:33"/>living life, and from that death raiſeth himſelf in his own power, then thou acteſt from the true living principle; for thou art crucified to the world, through the operation of Gods ſpirit, then thou art in unione with God, through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſus Chriſt, which was Gods mercy letten down in the power of that word, and by that power did cauſe a death in thee, to bring forth himſelf in thee; thou declaring by acting mercifulneſſes that thon art in God, he in thee; ſo an uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne a marriage is made, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thee and God, by the living word of his power; that cauſes ſuch an effectual death, to cauſe his glorious life, in thee to raign in glory unto himſelf.</p>
            <p>So beloved, You ſee that man is nothing but paſſive, in propriety of ſpeech, and nothing but God is mans free all.</p>
            <p>Now beloved thus I prove it, thus man had, nor hath, no true origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality but in God; for forth from him, in the power of his word were we created; there was our firſt ſtate, in created appearances; well, we no ſooner were men, but we were in need of mercy; for I ſay that the created was tyed upon the obedience, which obedience implies, and cannot be denyed, but there is ſome wanting, and then not perfection in mans firſt ſtate created. Now I ſhall brethren diſcover to you through Gods mercy, that, that is hid to the ſons of men; I beſeech you minde for Jeſus ſake, theſe words are perfect in their center. Thus, Jeſus is the Saviour, which is but thus much, the declarative of Gods mercy; Now I prove by reaſon, and you ſhall all be witneſs to what I ſay, and let no mans paſſion be prevalent over his underſtanding; thus God gave forth a Creation, Now minde, God gave in that creation a life that was not created, neither could nor never can detract. This is in the whole Creation, in every figure living; and accounted dead with us: for there is in every appearance a living life, that though it is the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> yet it is not of the body, nor receiveth from the body; but 'tis it ſelf raigning in all ſtorms and tempeſts in man, which thing is typifyed out, in that typication of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw it, it lies within the inmoſt vail, which muſt not be lookt upon, no the high-Prieſt muſt go into that vail but once a year. That was thus much typified, that, that one yeer was a time, repreſenting every one intire figure or man, that muſt be looked upon at the time in Gods mercy.</p>
            <p>Now beloved, That time of Gods looking into that inmoſt vail of ours, 'tis I may ſay, the opening all the other vails; and that is our departing from this world, and then he takes that living life of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into himſelf, for that is the divine nature that cannot detract his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; this is Gods figure in man, for minde who is it ſaith, <hi>Let us make man in our own image,</hi> ſaith the Bible or riddle. Now them words are falſly tranſlated.</p>
            <p>I will inſert the true Text. <hi>Anni Elohim Sambah allu ſalvah in re,</hi> them two words of Latin, are to make the full import in the ſtate.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170906:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The true declared text is this, Be thou like me in the humanity of my Creation. Beloved Brethren, in that ſtate <hi>Re</hi> lies the import, it is the Creation, for we count <hi>Re</hi> a thing, and <hi>Re</hi> is Gods Creation, that is Gods thing.</p>
            <p>Now to open the meaning of theſe words to the learned; though as the Lord lives, I neither can, or ever could read, any Hebrew, or Greek or any tongues but Engliſh; neither do I know any Hebrew but my own Characters, and them I had all in one day, before night. I could write them, but knew not the meaning of any one of them; onely it was ſaid to me by the Spirit, they were Hebrew, and then my corrupt minde deſired to be ſatisfied by man, and then he ſaid they were ſo: but this was weakneſs in me, and ſin as you account it; but I beſeech you give me leave to declare to the learned, the meaning of the words in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew; The copy I inſert in his proper Radiaſes intire as the were firſt wrote in; there was but ſeven Characters, for Scholars if you truly know ſeven in his origini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that is perfection <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter is <hi>Sambah,</hi> or your <hi>Samech,</hi> the next is <hi>Thau,</hi> you ſay many times <hi>Tau,</hi> the third is <hi>Koph,</hi> the fourth is <hi>Mem,</hi> the fifth is <hi>Jod,</hi> you ſay <hi>Joth,</hi> the ſixth is <hi>Pe,</hi> the ſeventh is <hi>Caph;</hi> now Scholers you admire if highly read, or elſe you cannot admire; for as God the glorious Creator, in whoſe preſence we all are, I in my maſters majeſty declare the very ſame Characters, as was let down to the firſt created by God, and the true demonſtration of the fore cited Text is the full import to and of the minde of God.</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Kaph</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I will cleer your judgement; (I ſpeak to you high and learned ones) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the impead, in the perfection, now how can an impead be, in perfection? no it cannot be, but thus it is, perfection takes fleſhly appearances to act in, and appearances is perfection, there <hi>Kaph</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in that ſtate is no impead, becauſe ſhe is a ſtate ſtated in perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Now in her letting down, ſhe and all the reſt is but one perfection, and every one in them is perfections; but when we come to place them, to underſtand by them, they become countable or numeral. But I paſs to other matter of concernment.</p>
            <p>But beloved, To make a cleer diſcovery in the point, in the Image of God in man, thus, God ſaid, be thou like me in the humanity of my Creation, now I beſeech you minde.</p>
            <p>The ſame that ſaid, Be thou like me, was let down to us ſenſible creatures, for the ſenceable is next of God, ſo I may ſay is not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſound, for God is the ſubſtance; of and from his ſubſtance, all things and appearances is but ſounds, for beloved, we are but ſounds, or figures of that ſubſtance; which is God in every ſound, for know there is nothing that ſounds, but God is the ſubſtance of that ſound, now beloved, I beſeech you minde the trouble that comes to us, it troubles us becauſe we are but ſounds, but the ſubſtance is not troubled, neither
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170906:34"/>Brethren, when our ſounds are taken into him, that is the ſubſtance of all things, that is Chriſt or God; then we are at reſt, becauſe our ſounds or ſhadows are in the ſubſtance, in which ſubſtance is perpetual reſt; for I beſeech you minde, that that truly is, cannot ſuffer, but that that is not, is that ſuffers; for there is nothing that can properly be ſaid to be, but God, and he is unione; therefore in him all have reſt, for he is the center of reſt to all and all things. Now you will object and ſay, that wicked men they have no reſt in God: Minde your own words, God doth create all, and nothing can create it ſelf, then know that God is the fountain whence all iſſued out.</p>
            <p>Now then preſently you will catch and ſay, that I ſay wickedneſs come from God, becauſe I will give you more hold before I conſute your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and make a cleer diſtinct betwixt God and ſin.</p>
            <p>Thus, minde, I lay down the rule, that ſhall cauſe the product. Firſt there was no ſin, for ſay you, God was alone, 'tis granted, But ſay I that God created all things, and ſin as you account it, is in that thing that God made. Now I ſay if God had not made man or Angel, they could not have ſinned, I ſpeak your own term ſin, though I know what ſin is, now had there not been a ſeeming ſomething, there could not have been a ſound of ſomething: and indeed that ſeeming ſomething is but a ſound, and that ſound nothing; then where is that that is but a ſound of that nothing?</p>
            <p>So I beſeech you minde, <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherit eternal life,</hi> that Text is almoſt full read from the originality of its root or radi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, the Text. <hi>Ante ſelem in re ſabat alli jah in huri beneam ſallu ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</hi> The true words rendred in full to a tittle.</p>
            <p>The earthly man is corrupt and cannot ſtand in light, them very words are the true import of the Text in his true originality.</p>
            <p>Now I will ſhow you the odds or difference in thoſe two citations, your tranſlation ſaith, <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherit eternal life;</hi> now I ſay the earthly man is corrupt, and cannot ſtand in light: now where is theſe Texts variation? no where: though the words alter much, for both the Texts concludes, that that is not cannot be. There the ſcope is full weighed, but the words vary in expreſſion, thus: fleſh and blood is not the earthly man, for fleſh and blood is, when the life of that fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man is gone: now know that without the life that is abſent, fleſh and blood could not be acted.</p>
            <p>Now minde, for the earthly man carries in it, whatſoever was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive (as you call it, and that cannot ſtand in light, for 'tis all darkneſs in which the light was hid, and the light then is taken into light, and the earthly man which is meant the ſerpentine knowledge, in that earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly body, for fleſh and blood is not knowledge; for fleſh and blood is, when life and knowledge of the natural man is gone: So you ſee there is more, then fleſh and blood to be underſtood in that Text, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170906:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>of man-ſhall not enter into eternal life, as well as fleſh and blood, but the life of theſe lives, is taken into God; for (as with reverence I may ſpeak to his divine Majeſty) 'tis part of himſelf, nay all him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; in that appearance both part and all, and all things, this is God our Saviour, taking us into himſelf, theſe words time cannot bear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locking, that is concerning Chriſt, for Chriſt is not yet known; the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery lies in theſe words, Chriſt ſhall come in the glory of his fathers wiſdom, and knowledge is with him, nay himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you weigh ſeriouſly, If the ſubſtance of man be but a noiſe of his own center, as that life doth plainly manifeſt, which is our ſole, and that word is tranſlated ſoul; Now minde the difference in them two words, and the full import of both; and of either diſtincts, For foul is properly Gods eſſence derivative, eſſenced in fleſh, now know that ſole is our being in darkneſs, that is without the diſcovered light of God riſen in us, for they are no more agreeable to one another, then light to darkneſs; for the one holds the natural man, the other the ſpiritual light in that natural man; but the word <hi>ſol,</hi> is read form ſoul, and ſoul is read for <hi>ſole;</hi> being derived from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof,</hi> holds an infinire, and a definitire, being the ſecond orig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ni in the declared ſtrength, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sambah</hi> firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof,</hi> next. Now know Scholar, that the infinitire is read when <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof,</hi> ſtands radical, that is the firſt let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or leading letter; let <hi>kof</hi> be placed the third radical, then he is read definitire, the word that is the ancient Hebraick word is <hi>oukſi,</hi> that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitire, now the word infinitire, in the virgin ſtate, in the true orthodox Hebraick is <hi>Keva,</hi> now in this word there muſt be underſtood <hi>ad infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de faciendam in re,</hi> that is to ſay, To the infiniteneſs, a making a thing, that is ſole to the ſoul, though ſoul is the proper eſſence, or life of ſole, thus intricate is Jehovahs ways, and every work do him praiſe, think you what you will; even that, that is the Creterriſed noiſe, that you count ſin, 'tis God his greateſt praiſe though it be but a noiſe from the Creature, and nothing in nor to God, for ſin keeps men under from breaking forth into outrages, which they both, are but the noiſe of the Creature, for God cannot be pleaſed, nor angry, for if pleaſed not God, if angry not God; for God Is, and that is God, but how? neither angry nor pleaſed, both angry and pleaſed, and yet all this is but one Is, and that is God, for know, all that can be ſaid of God he Is, or I am; or the all of all things.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the perfect theory of God. Now minde you great learned ones, that inwrap the poor blinde and ignorant ones, within the ſwaddle-bands of your own invention, tying them to your ſelves to ride on, the maxim will hold, now though I am unlearned, in what I declare for I am not well engliſhed, for many words I underſtand not; neither have I memory. Now you cannot ſay to me, as was ſaid to <hi>Paul, Much learning hath made him mad;</hi> now I ſay, and many know, that by mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170906:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>I came to knowing, and in time God will make me ſpeak plain knowledge, that by all ſhall be acknowledged, not onely <hi>England,</hi> but many Lands and Nations.</p>
            <p>But Scholars, my Teacher hath no books, nor I have none to read, neither will I, for my Teacher is Is, that is God, now ye Prieſts, my brethren by Creation cannot be denyed, to come to Gods perfect <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologi</hi> the Engliſh is Gods light declared in Creations, now I begin. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>los in re arkad el.</hi> That is a ſhort ſtate, then if you have true light, it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viewed in a ſhort ſcope, but Scholars, 'tis wrote in the golden nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merals, that is the golden numbers ruled rule, being five ſignificants, but though unlearned, I will give you the true expoſition, now thus I prove it to be truth, minde, I return a ſtrange anſwer that hath not been returned in multitudes of ages that is this. I know they are both true becauſe I know neither of them falſe, by reaſon that I have not knowledge; therefore the thing is, that is God.</p>
            <p>Now you curious Scholars will ſay I have cited the words, but not the derivacy or Engliſh of them, and ſpeak of two and both true: Thus I ſaid it was the golden number; and in propriety of method, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivacy comes after; though it lies in it own life, in the root; but I will declare the words again, and the Engliſh by them; you will ſay 'tis falſe, I know it is true. <hi>Selos in re arkad el,</hi> That is thus much, heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmation is in and from God; now what word is it hold both a Negative and an Affirmative diſtributive? I will tell you, the word is <hi>arkad,</hi> being wrote <hi>in moyhes,</hi> in the meadiſh method <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>k</hi> bares the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſud ſtate, and yet the radical leader in that ſtate, the word ſtands ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, or bar'd by reaſon of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>kof,</hi> for minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>kof</hi> or <hi>k</hi> raiſes into the third maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, now that word <hi>arkad</hi> is the golden number, as proper as the whole ſtate ſtated, for 'tis a Negative and an Affirmative diſtributive, that is the whole maxim or foundation of the golden number, you Scholars here is one glimpſe of my next coming forth, for though I ceaſe for a time, 'tis to come in more power, this I know ſo ſure as the Lord lives, to the confounding all men; therefore, though I be detracted for a time 'tis to come and drown all your learning; for it is a derivacy from the Greek tongue, it is that whore that hath made all Nation, drunk with the wine, but winde is the propriety in ſpeech, for the Greek Teſtament hath made the Nations drunk with the wine of her fornication. <hi>Jeſous Chriſtos hook die et in eternitas et in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oternitates ſalem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ bat el a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le mem:</hi> Joſus Chriſt to day and for ever to eternity ſuffering, and no end; for judge ye, Chriſt ſuffers us in our unthankfulneſs, and yet taketh us into his reſt, which is perfection, this is the ſcope of the whole Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; but thon where will be had a ſtipend for this whore the New-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that <hi>John</hi> ſaw, riſen out of the bottomleſs pit, for to maintain her pride in skarle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that is the bloody robe; that hath had in origini out of the New-Teſtament, if not as we are in judgement; put to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170906:36"/>death: when the Goſpel is to be pittiful, to the blinde and ignorant, ſo in truth the Goſpel is onely a lye, made by men to fetch about their deſigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England,</hi> you have the greateſt ſeal to ſet to this, to make the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt impreſſion, when the truth in the Goſpel is mercy, pity, Juſtice, but look I beſeech you, you great ones.</p>
            <p>O how for God, and the Goſpel, when your hearts went after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing; and God gave you prevalency to declare your own hearts, and then by acts you have declared, that you never intended what you declared; but have made your lye to ſtand, but it lies a lye open to the view of all Nations, for you have forgotten the living God; and imbrace Gods of gold, and ſilver, Lands, and in heritances; that you ſhall not hold (minde them words) and the maxim I prove it by, is this, take notice all people; Gods glory he will not give to another, and wo unto us in <hi>England,</hi> we have clothed our actings with the name of Goſpel while we were weak; and when we were ſtrong, we in the face of the Sun, have declared that we were hypocrites, crying that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name Goſpel to make it a ſtalking horſe to accompliſh our own covetous wicked ends.</p>
            <p>O actions in <hi>England,</hi> I in the preſence of God do call for your teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which is murther, oppreſſion, and deceit; now I demand if theſe fruit grow upon that root that you &amp; I my ſelf held forth to the people, which we ſaid was for the glory of the Goſpel, liberty, law, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; do you remember all theſe named ſnares, the word is proper, for the end is the cleer manifeſter of our heart acting, and God is the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſoul, I lye not.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee our purchaſe purchaſed, by this we have attracted, we in power by your own ſtrength, are murderers of that number murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their blood, and the cry of their diſtreſſed ones, both joyn in one crying for vengeance againſt you, your eſtate is their blood, your bread is their blood, you eat and drink the blood of them you have cruelly murthered: I prove it thus, We all ingage in the reality of our hearts for one abſolute good, the thing is good in it ſelf, good to all and all poſterity, by our combinining together the end is effected: Now our loſs is great in lives and eſtates. Now comes the winding up, That crowns our labour, and it is wound quite contrary to moſt that ingaged, and a few make prey to themſelves by another way that the reſt never thought upon: Now in this act they have brought upon them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the blood ſhed, and are robbers of all the reſt, and ſtand indicted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord for to anſwer for the fact; yet beloved, let me tell you, your ſafety with my own lies now in theſe men, and you are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>und to uphold theſe men; for you have a being amongſt theſe men, and if the other prevail, as the Lord lives you ſhall neither have being nor breath amongſt them, now God will purge theſe men himſelf, this I know.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170906:36"/>
            <p> But beloved, the time haſtens on that Iſrael ſhall return to his own Land. O beloved cry unto our God, that he may hear and have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us, for our bondage in fleſh and ſpirit is very great. O for thy ſake O Iſrael I have forſaken all, I have emptyed my ſelf to ſupport thy children and in thy work. <hi>O ſepe peon alu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſele et terra in re et in me.</hi> O Jeruſalem my joy, thou art my ſorrow in earth: <hi>Non tempus orrattah ellah ſallu edereat alpi ſele mem:</hi> 'Tis not time for me to deliver thee.</p>
            <p>But thy deliverance my eyes in this fleſh ſhall ſee thee in glory and majeſty. <hi>O pall penan alli neat allu perereat allu Jah ſede ſophim.</hi> The Lord thy God will reſtore thee in the pinch of time in mercy, when thy people are throughly purged from iniquity that they may weigh Gods mercy at a true value. <hi>O apolinariam in ſabine</hi> L. Then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall praiſe the Lord and ſing unto him in glory and dignity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved what is here ſpoken, the Prophets my brethren have confirmed and affirmed, that the Lord will make good his promiſe to the whole houſe of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>Beloved, this day I declare to you my <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> that is I hope reſt to my ſelf, for I ſhall now be ſilent for a ſeaſon, in which my ſpirit rejoyces, but 'tis but the retracting for a time, for to ſpeak in a higher light, in the divine and Evangelical expreſſing, for the work of God ſhall ſtand, in which work I know I muſt labour, for the Lords harveſt is great in <hi>England,</hi> for brethren you poor dejected ones, you caſt off ones; you, even you ſhall rejoyce, for our redemption haſtens, and the time is neer; but ſuch ſorrow and troubles is at hand to the worldly men, that the like hath not been in any age ſince man inhabited the Globe. This I know by the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>My next reſurrection ſhall come in Print ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Called <hi>Theaurau-John,</hi> his ſecond part of his <hi>Theous-Ori Appokolipical,</hi> or Gods light declared in myſteries.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Theaurau-John Tanniour allah al,</hi> High-Prieſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb facs="tcp:170906:37"/>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170906:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>March</hi> 6. 1650. Poſitions to the Clergy, ſo called; Or, The Prieſts, ſo called.</head>
            <p>Know there is a name and a thing, and all names are no thing, and God is the Thing, and all things are but the name of that Thing; For when you leave <hi>una, in duo</hi> is the Creation, for Jehovah his opening is the creating the Creations.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is that God ye teach to the people?</p>
            <p n="2">2 What is he you your ſelves affirm ye know?</p>
            <p n="3">3 What is the humanity of Chriſt in his firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in his ſecond principle, and in his third prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that is fleſh? I have half opened this ſtate for you.</p>
            <p n="4">4 What ſtories do you teach out of your own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for the divine truth?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Now you have done this, how came you by your holy calling as you call it? but know call is a lye, and ſo are ye Prieſts that are not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daxed in your foundation, and the intendant foundation is God.</p>
            <p n="6">6 What is the heighth you attain in your learned learning? This I anſwer my ſelf, to ſhow you 'tis the learned lying lye. Now that is the heigth your ſtudyed lye can reach, for a lye reaches a lye, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="7">7 What is the Celebrating the body of Jeſus as you call it?</p>
            <p n="8">8 What is the Deity in the humany, that can or could be offered up?</p>
            <p n="9">9 What is the trine of Sol, in the humane part of this terreſtial body?</p>
            <p n="10">10 What is the operation of the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Sol?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170906:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> 11 What is the influx in the Trine of <hi>Sol?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 What is the Dameter in the Sea?</p>
            <p n="13">13 What is meant by the bands of Orion ſpoken of in <hi>Job?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 What is <hi>Venus</hi> her operation in the <hi>Moon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 What is light in its eſſential being from God? Search deely, 'tis not the Sun.</p>
            <p n="16">16 What involveth the Waters into the great deep? The ſecondary cauſe I require.</p>
            <p n="17">17 What is the inlet to theſe, and the knowledge in them? You ſay God: Minde what follows, then your anſwer excludes Man; and in this ſtate man is but dead earth: for the things of God are revealed in truth by his Spirit in Man, and not Man.</p>
            <p n="18">18 What is the Deity in the humanity?</p>
            <p n="19">19 What is Chriſt the Son in the Trinity operative?</p>
            <p n="20">20 What is the Virgin that brought forth Emanuel or Jeſus?</p>
            <p n="21">21 What is <hi>Addam</hi> in the Garden?</p>
            <p n="22">22 What is <hi>Rebecka</hi> that brought forth <hi>Iſaack?</hi> Know, all temporals are Hieroglyphicks Celeſtial.</p>
            <p n="23">23 What is the Trine in the Deity that is placed in humanity?</p>
            <p n="24">24 What is the influx in the Celeſtial ſpheres in every generation, and Creation Created?</p>
            <p n="25">25 What is the intendant in truth in this figure <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>?</p>
            <p n="26">26 What influences from the Celeſtial bodies inheres in us?</p>
            <p n="27">27 What is the influe in the Matrickx and womb in the Morning?</p>
            <p n="28">28 What is the tranſcendency in the Aurora?</p>
            <p n="29">29 What is the ſtays in the watery world or <hi>Abyſs Orbis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30 What is the inherent in the Philiades?</p>
            <p n="31">31 What is the Sperm in the whole Creation in the Generator?</p>
            <p n="32">32 What is the influx that cauſes the procreated in the <hi>tertia loca;</hi> or bottom?</p>
            <p n="33">33 What is the inherent inclue in the Trine of <hi>Sol?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">34 What is the Radicak radack in the Lunan conſtellative, or the conſtellative of the <hi>Moon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35 What is the inlet into the Philiades in his operative part?</p>
            <p n="36">36 What is the Tobaſs Celeſtial, or alclu in the ſpheres in their Trines Celeſtial?</p>
            <p n="37">37 What is the end of all Querie from God to man, from man to God, from both to one?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170906:38"/>
            <head>MY ANSWER Added to the CHARGE againſt Me.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough the great Calumny of aſperſion laid upon me, I am forced to publiſh to the world what I have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and withal I have added my Defence againſt the copy of my Indictment: that the Book it ſelf will manifeſtly declare how they have traduced my words through ignorance or envy; what I did declare, and this is a command, <hi>Thou ſhall not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy neighbour. And in judgement and righteouſneſs onely ſhalt thou ſwear: For I am a holy God, and will viſit the falſe ſwearer.</hi> I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted all the points in the copy of the Indictment.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They charge me with <hi>A diſſoluteneſs in living, and breaking all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſociety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for living, that is, obeying what God hath commanded; know that no man is perfect, but there is a cloſure and conſenting to all that is commanded; which is declared by outward actings, and for that I ſhall not deſire any favour at any mans hand; but this, I deſire you to ſearch
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170906:39"/>my life in actions thtorowly, and I ſhall prove unto you a Looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs, whereby you may diſcern your own ſpots and foulneſs, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful failings. So much for the firſt Charge.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond Charge is, <hi>That I deny Goſpel-Ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, That I do not nor cannot, for the Ordinances of the Goſpel are in truth, the power of God; upon whom ſoever it light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it maketh them obedient to the commands of God, and that is love diſtributive, and to that I ſay I was forced to make a diſtribution a releaſing and a ſatisfaction; now this was Goſpel in power, which pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you my perſecuters know not; for ye have the name Goſpel, but the power of it is not known unto you; for then you would love the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, help the needy; but alas, your Goſpel lies in your head by parrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learning, and not in the heart, wrote by <hi>digitus Dei in Cor allah,</hi> that is, the Goſpel is not in your hearts, writ by the finger of God; for if it were, perſecution would ceaſe, and acts of mercy would flow, and deceit va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; your conſtant gueſt, or conſtant inmate. So much for the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The third was, That I ſaid, <hi>That the Bible was a riddle.</hi> And I leave it to the world to judge of; is it not a riddle, a myſtery, a Microcoſm to the world; nay to you? if not a riddle and a thing that you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not; wherefore is not obedience due unto it rendered; for you make it worſe then I do: For a riddle is as proper a word as myſtery, but you make it a lye, by your not obeying the things therein comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and declare your ſelf-actions to be truer then that? for if you know it to be true, wherefore not adored by you? But ye cry the name Goſpel high, but you are a Goſpel to your ſelf-ends, for the truth in the Goſpel is doing deeds of mercy, and not in diſputing names of dead let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and for the tranſlations, they are falſe in many places, and one thing ſtated for another thing intended; that many knows.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The fourth is, that I ſhould ſay <hi>That there is no ſuch thing as Hell, as your Miniſters hold forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will ſee in my Book what is ſpoken to it. But I ſay Hell is not as the Miniſters hold it forth, neither as it is denoted in your inſert: Hell is a ſeparation from an enjoyment; and give you the definition, and that is all that can be ſaid: but I refer you to the Book, to ſee what I have ſaid, and know that there is nothing, but muſt be denoted in word, and then the main Quere is, What that word doth include in it ſelf, and what the ſpirit doth intend in that word? it is not what we conceive to be, but what it in truth in it ſelf is, and thus none but the Spirit is able to make forth or define.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Fifthly, That I ſaid <hi>The ſoul of man is eſſencied in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay firſt, There is a God, that cannot be denyed, then this God eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſencying himſelf in every created appearance; and again, all theſe appearances eſſencyed in God doth appear from theſe words, <hi>In him we live, and move, and have our being;</hi> now Prieſts your rule will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170906:39"/>thus: know nothing below himſelf can bear or hold a ſtate in competition with the Lord, who is all, and yet nothing, this is Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, who is nothing, and yet the thing in things, not of the things, nor by the things, but he the life of all things, and he in regency and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſency, and in derivacy, and definacy, and ſtill he is unmoveable, always, for ever to come the ſame, and yet Jehovah cyphered is his name; here is one of my makka demical expreſſions, allegorically alluding to the point, into which all points; but to come down from this ſphear, God is a ſpirit, you ſay the ſoul is a ſpirit, I will be one with the ſimple, or I will dwell with the meek ſpirit, ſaith the Lord: now how is a ſpiritual dwelling? not to be defined by natural men, for they hear and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, ſo ſaith the true Scripture: a ſpiritual dwelling is being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely one, for theſe bodies of clay hold us at a diſtance, as witneſs the ſpirit derivative in its growing to be in unione, that is into the Eſſence, regency, in theſe words the ſtate lies, we groan and would be unclothed, that mortality might be ſwallowed up of life, theſe are both pointing to that oneneſs which is in God in unione. Now know that the ſoul is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual light, and light is God; now by this rule, envy, would ſay I ſay that the ſoul is God: no, 'tis in us a derivative from God, eſſencied in God, and at the unmoddeling every figure its figured in, returns to the eſſence Regina or God raigning, and is one in the unione in glory, tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for ever, now know in a ſpiritual being, that is light, it is in oneneſs with that great light, it came forth from this One; or God letting down his oneneſs, cauſed that oneneſs to appear in appearances; now the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances retracted, the oneneſs is received into himſelf, ſo then that light in the derivacy is taken into the eſſences regency, and then unione, a beginning, and an end; no end, but a beginning, neither beginning nor end, but the middle, and that is the center, and that is God in his reigning all.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That I did ſay that <hi>The Old and New-Teſtament was falſe and interwoven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know, that is eaſily anſwered, for the whole printing is mans connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or interweaving together; and for the Tranſlation, it is falſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, I ſay ſo ſtill, and in the point of Jeſus our Saviour is the main.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I ſaid, <hi>That God muſt ſave the divel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſtate is altered to what I declare, my Book will ſhow it, I ſay, that Chriſt came to ſave men-devils, devils men; Chriſt ſaid as much, if duly underſtood, for <hi>I come not to call the righteous, but ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</hi> is there not in our underſtanding a devil in this word Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan? did not Chriſt ſay unto <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me Sathan,</hi> or devil get thee behind me? you know that there is but two ſpirits in your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as good and bad; then know, not of God, then of the devil; there is your ſtate ſtated ſhort. Make you what you will of it, 'tis
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170906:40"/>not what you conceive, but what it in truth is.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That I ſaid that <hi>God had juſt mercy to ſave all, and no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that ſaith the contrary, is a blaſphemer, for I ſay God had juſt ſtrength to create, and not a tittle more; and juſt mercy to ſave his created, and not a tittle more: what a height in Chriſts School are ye, ſeeing that this is a paradox to you! I need not go no further for to ſearch the reaſon of your dark actions, for if you did know God, you muſt know him to be juſt, and juſt is perfection, and perfections is juſt, for if he were in himſelf more or leſs, then know he could not be perfect, or if he were more at one time then at another, he could not be juſt, and God is a juſt God, and holy perfect God: and becauſe you do not know God as he is in himſelf; but you have a God of your own gotten by learning and by hearing therefore, you perſecute them whom God hath taught himſelf, and planted himſelf in by his ſpirit of light.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That I ſaid that <hi>the New-Teſtament is a lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in the truth of true ſpeech it is, for you ſay, It is the holy Goſpel of Chriſt, and the holy word of God; and I ſay, It is but a name of dead letters ſet together with much interweaving of mans invention: and more, many places tranſlated to hold up the Pope and the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies ſupremacie, and burdening the People to their tyranny, and It is not Unione in it ſelf, therefore not Gods declarative in truth of name, for a name is but a ſhadow of a ſubſtance, which ſubſtance is Chriſt the Lord, you underſtand me not, nor one in ten millions knows not truly what Chriſt is, nay not one in the Creation; (now are you ſtound or are amazed) I will prove it againſt all oppoſers; therefore 'tis not looking for an outward Chriſt, at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but a living life of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs within your ſelves, that gives you ſight towards Chriſt; this you ſay 'tis the word of God, and I ſay 'tis dead letters ſet together; and is that whore that hath deceived the Nations, now know that truth which is Gods Goſpel of peace to the ſoul, is not got by hearing an outward name named by a Prieſt; for naming what God hath done in me, cannot confer the ſubſtance thing to you, which is Chriſt in the ſoul: the name doth deceive you, but the ſubſtance cannot; for it is Gods ſtrength, that is, Chriſt the Lord, taking you into himſelf; then that is true Goſpel not wrote in and upon Paper, but upon the ſoul of man, but my book will open it, in the firſt and ſecond part, to the full view of all men; here lies the ſtate, you ſay that the Teſtament is the word God, I ſay it is but the name of the word of God, and much falſe ſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in it, and I ſay God is the word himſelf, converting you without that written word, by his free mercy, which is Chriſt a ſubſtance and not a lettered name, for you may learn the name and deceive your ſelvs not having the thing, which is Chriſt the ſubſtance converting you unto himſelf: now I ſpeak Allegorically, and you underſtand literally, ſo you wrong me, and cauſe my true innocent and harmleſs intention to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170906:40"/>ſuffer. Brethren, let us not fall out in names, but let us live honeſtly in things.</p>
            <p n="10">10 I ſaid that he that added or diminiſhed to the Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> there is a curſe ſtated on them, which I ſay is not in the truly true original, but added by the Pope to cauſe an adorative worſhip to be tendred to he knew not what, and that is blaſphemy: thus, for man to ſtate a word to cauſe obedience to that word ſtated, is blaſphemy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſtated in the ſeat of God and is not God; and this is the whole book called holy, and 'tis an Idol robbing God of his glory, for there is none holy but the Lord, and no created or made thing is holy, but God alone; where is your holy named Goſpel in letters? there is not two holies, but one holy, that is God; and holy is not names of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but the Lord living by his ſpirit in the ſouls of men, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined. Brethren, out of love, not for lucre of gain, have I communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated what God hath made known unto me; and my deſire is, that you ſhould not ſhut your eyes againſt the light, preferring your own reaſon and ſelf-will, wedded to the letter, of whoſe tranſlation you know no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: ye ſhall all be taught of me, ſaith the Lord, but you will have your God out of them written dead names called Scripture.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And that I ſaid that <hi>there is neither election nor reprobation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I ſay ſtill, for know, God Is, and Is is no chuſer or refuſer, but Is: ſearch you that out. Onely I give you this Query, How could God chuſe, when all was wrapped in the womb of unione? you ſay, From all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: declare you the product, and then I will anſwer, for in this ſtate I lye barred in unione without product.</p>
            <p n="12">12 They ſay that I ſaid, that <hi>God was not for ever.</hi> Which I proteſt I never ſpoke, and though it is not lawful for to draw conſequences to prove or produce evidences, yet in your own Charge, you ſay that I ſaid, The ſoul was of the eſſence of God, and ſay that the ſoul cannot ſuffer; minde what you make; that is the ſoul God: in denying what I truly ſpoke; for that that cannot ſuffer is a God, for all things muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer but one thing, and that is God, and the ſuffering of all things to that God is the due homage they ow unto God as he is their Liege Lord. Now I ſay before all men, you my accuſers are blaſphemers, and I am not; but rage not, I can paſs it by, God give you more light to ſee the beauty of his excellency, that you and I and the whole body may be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into one, then peace.</p>
            <p n="13">13 I ſaid that <hi>God was neither angry when men did ill, nor pleaſed when they did well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye weak Babes, who in your weakneſs do ye liken God unto? Is he like man? The loweſt of men? Nay weakeſt men, I deſire you to bring anger, and ſee how you can make it ſtand in Gods perfection, and bring pleaſing to Gods juſtneſs, and ſee how it will ſtand there. Thus if God can be angry in his eſſencial eſſence, I ſay he is no God, for anger is
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170906:41"/>weakneſs, and God Is, and that is all ſtrength, and therefore no anger, what can God be pleaſed in his eſſencial eſſence? then no God; for God is neither pleaſed nor angry, both pleaſed and angry, and yet neither pleaſed nor angry; for God Is, and Is is God: here is a myſtery that is not made known to the ſons of men, unto which I ſhall not ſpeak at this time; onely know, that in perfection there is neither pleaſed nor anger, for more or leſs, not perfection, I am, that is perfection; therefore ye ſons of <hi>Jacob</hi> are not conſumed.</p>
            <p n="14">14 And that I ſaid that <hi>Sin is Gods higheſt praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, ſin is weakneſs, which is the creature in his corrupt eſtate, now comes light from God, and doth caſt forth this ſin or weakneſs, and then plants light: then from that that was dark, that is ſin did raign, there grace doth raign to the glory of God in a tranſcendent meaſure, becauſe 'tis the work of the third perſon, but the unione ſpirit if not ſinful, we needed no mercy: from ſin obſtruction is righteouſneſs raigning, and ſo ſin doth eloſterate the ſtrength of Gods mercy, and Gods mercy doth eloſterate ſin to the full viewing of its ugly deformity; this is ſafe, nay your own Scripture, for we being taken into light, praiſe God for our deliverance, that is redeemed from death, and placed in life, then we value Gods mercy and not before.</p>
            <p n="15">15 And that I ſaid <hi>God was little before the fall, and the fall of man did raiſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this point is clean traduced, and never ſuch a word ſpoken, as the Epiſtle will ſhow.</p>
            <p>The point was this, that it is ſaid that man fallen was to be raiſed to a greater glory, now I demand what greater glory could man be raiſed unto, when man was wrapped in the eſſence of God before he came forth in appearance? you muſt hold in all Gods declaratives him to be the perfection, ſo man can but be raiſed to the ſame ſtate, and no more; for God is neither greater nor leſs but always one always the ſame.</p>
            <p>Brethren, had you been in the Goſpel as you are too much in the name of it, not knowing the ſubſtance, you would have commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſufferings, not perſecuting me without a cauſe; but God is juſt, and in his good time he will reſtore my breach. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.33. <hi>Sell that ye ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and give almes,</hi> have you not read thus? but who practiſes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the command? Yours to ſerve you and the Nation.</p>
            <p>Now know all people, That blaſphemy is this, and no other, that is, for man to deny trine or Trinity, and Unity in Trinity, and there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blaſphemy; as thus, for man to ſay that there is no God, and for man to deny the operative Trine or Trinity, theſe are accounted blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and there is no other. Now you are not to draw conſequences to prove or produce evidences, for if not denying in plain Engliſh words the God or Godhead thus named, though no man living knows what it is, yet in that ſtate it ſtands ſtated, that if any man ſhall deny
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170906:41"/>the Trinity and Unity in Trinity it is death by the Law, and do you but read thus, that the Sun is of the Father is blaſphemy, in our Engliſh tongue, for of is a Negative proper in our Engliſh writing, though you read it an Affirmative, would you be glad to ſuffer for wrong pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ncing God? no, the Law requires it not; but 'tis the devil, envy got into the heart and head of the notional called Chriſtians, now before this time you have heard me diſclaim the word Of, as it is in print in my Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Anroran Tranlagorum.</hi> For God hath cauſed me to write all, and not ſpeak to diſpute, you are my witneſſes now I come and refer you to your belief, that is thus written, and the Catholick Faith is thus, That we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one God in Trinity and in Unity and Unity in Trinity, ſaith the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there is one perſon of the Father, another of the Son, &amp; another of the holy Ghoſt; there is the Negative denying the Affirmative in that ſtate, I prove it thus: the Father is one, the Son is one, and the holy Ghoſt is one; and not three ones, but one onely one, who is the all three in unione. Brethren, I deſire that this main maxim in divinity may be reſolved, though ſtated by the mad man, thus: How you can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert from a ſpiritual unione, a perſon or from a ſpiritual Trine, three perſons, for know you that in the ſpiritual eſſence, that there can be no perſon, and yet three intire ones, and theſe three, one in unione; and this Trinity I ſhall ſpeak a little to, what is diſcovered to me in this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and refer it unto them that have a clearer eye and deeper judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for God hath confounded my knowledge as a man, but as my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is that truth may flouriſh, and that miſt we are in; received by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from <hi>Rome,</hi> as our Books are too full of their ſubtile pointings, which I ſee plainly, and in this that I ſhall ſpeak to is the main. Firſt, know that there is one eſſencial offence, from whence all things deſcenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſcended into created appearances, this is undenyable by any. Now to ſtate this eſſence in a perſon, 'tis to confine, nay viliſie the living life it ſelf; for know that the living life in the whole Creation cannot be perſon, but ſpirit; now God is a Spirit, therefore no perſon; judge ye for God Is, and Is Is God, that is all can be ſpoken; ſo much for the Father, the Son is <hi>Secundus viva vita,</hi> the ſecond living life in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Now know that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the life of the world.</hi> Now I would not have you think that I intend that that Jeſus that you account and I know ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that he as he was then, was the life of the world, but the light of life in the ſoul of that Jeſus as he was one with the Father in the regency or raigning eſſence; ſo and no other was he the life of the Creation; do not deceive your ſelves with a body of your own earth, the Son of God was this upon whom thou ſeeſt the Spirit deſcend, that is he this was ſpoken to <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>Now brethren, I would not have you to ſtate an adorative opinion, upon the Books called Scripture; for know, that they were but wrote by men, and they themſelves point us to a higher diſcovery; that ſhall
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170906:42"/>be manifeſted, that is the calling the Jews, and the preaching the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel as it is ſaid in the laſt days ſaith God, <hi>I will pour out of my Spirit, and your ſons and daughters both old and yong ſhall Prophecy ſaith the Lord.</hi> And what height of myſtery is not yet known, nor how God will teach in the laſt days, is not manifeſted but in a tranſcendent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſhutting up the glory of the Law and Goſpel in a moſt glorious glory magniphiciencically expreſſing his truth out of both them dark vails ſo long by us contended for .<hi>Heva Aſſa al oli mem.</hi> This Hebrew ſtate I open not not that I want light.</p>
            <p>Brethren, ye prieſts ye would be always talking the converſion of the Jews, but you would never have it come to paſs as you have pratingly prayed for the converſion of the Jews, and now you begin to perſecute Us Jews, all this is becauſe, you are afraid your trade of lyes muſt down, now brethren, I would not have you be angry becauſe the Goſpel is love, if you be true Miniſters that is truly called, then know Chriſt hath preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in you this leſſon, <hi>Fly from anger.</hi> But I ſhall ſtate ſix Queries, to which you ſhall do well to anſwer, ye Prieſts my brethren.</p>
            <p>Firſt, How came the holy Apoſtolick calling conferred to you for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove this ſixteen hundred year together, and the world never knew nor heard of it, brethren, you are men that will hide nothing that may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the glory of your trade.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You muſt be Miniſters of Chriſts ſecond coming, and that is in greater ſigns and miracles then before, as all the Scriptures mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and what have any of you done, but tell us over dead names.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What have you to do to make a trade of the Apoſtles dead names, as to abuſe their writing in exhorſiſm, being you have not their ſpirit, that that was truth in them is a lye in you, for they were that ſpirit of which ye have and are but the dead name.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Ye deny the Scripture, making your ſelf-will Scripture, and under that name you cloak your covetouſneſs, and are perjured men, for <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain,</hi> and let all the people judge, do not you exact Tythes from your brethren, that Goſpel Miniſters have no warrant to do: So Gods word is taken in vain, becauſe his word is your colour to act your own will, and word, and Law in and by, he that but nameth Chriſt muſt depart from his evil way; and you preach Chriſt to maintain your evil way.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Whom Chriſt called and ſent, they never ſtudied, for the light of ſtudy is but the witch of the minde, deceiving the ſimple man in the ſame body, for know if by ſtudy Chriſt can be attained, then not Gods free gift, for God giveth wiſdom to the ſimple, and maketh the tongue of the ſtammerer ſpeak plainly myſterious myſteries, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned; this I know, and from ſenſe I ſpeak, this is a riddle to you, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaxk al Saby oli el dele mem,</hi> Who was my teacher here? None but the Lord: I read no books, though I am mad, I tell you by madneſs I am
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170906:42"/>inſtructed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was as ſerpentine wiſe as any of you, but God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it in me, me in it; and I am become a fool and a babe. <hi>Sed ſeloſe in Re aggarim el pethrat alvi ſene accorata.</hi> The Engliſh though I underſtand not the Latin nor Hebrew, here is another riddle, yet the Engliſh of that ſtate is this, But the heavenly light doth give light to view the deep myſteries of it ſelf in the terreſtrial Creation, now you will ſay, this mad man ſpeaks ſome Latin, ſome Hebrew, and ſome greek; and confound in broken words, this reaſon I render you, 'tis to confound you great ones, Rabbies I mean: Now know that the ſpirit is not confined, but ſpeaks one intire language in the whole Creation, combining and conjoyning all languages into one truth, what think you to that reaſon, is it not ſtrange? Now know that my teacher is my God who hath afflicted and broken me for his own uſe, to confound you and all men; for know, that in <hi>England Babel</hi> is a declining, and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs raigning.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Wherefore if ye were the Miniſters of Chriſt, do you flye to the ſecular power to defend your cauſe with their ſword, and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your cauſe to Chriſt, willingly rendring a reaſon of your Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intreated earneſtly thereunto. This know, that Chriſt you own, is a dead Chriſt as your ſelves declare, by reaſon that your ſtrength lies in the Magiſtrates ſword, now then ſpeak plainly, that we may know, that the Magiſtrate you ſerve, and his ſword is your Chriſt; nay I will give you a plainer definition, you are many of you Magiſtrates and Miniſters of Chriſt, but you hang him by your ſides, Are ye not turned mercina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Captains? Now ſhow me in your word of God, that ever your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt, whoſe ſervants ye pretend to be, ever preached with a ſword to convert men into another world, I deſire a Text in the word of God to bare out theſe actions, nay I pray you give me leave, you have got ſwords, that if now men will not pay Tythes, you are able to fetch them in your ſelves. I beſeech you bare with me if I tell you the truth, have we not all ingaged againſt Popery, and to ſhow the zeal we have againſt it, we have made holes in all our Church Windows, in ſhow of aboliſhment ye Stateſmen, this is but Mince and Commin, but the great thing of righteouſneſs is neglected, this day I ſay by your own Acts, Covenant and Engagement, That whomſoever in this Nation or in our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doth pay his Tythes according to what he did cuſtomary, that man or men are perjured perſons, and the Law of the Land requires their ears, and the Law of God they ſhall not eſcape; again, they that raign by forcing men to pay Tythes, are perjured by the Law and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they have made. I ſay, not I but the Lord, wo unto the perfide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous generation, that maketh a Covenant of deceit, and themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves, by the ſame Law. I beſeech you by the mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that this may be broke off, 'tis now time, and hightime to turn from evil, for the harveſt is ripe, and the ſickles is ready.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170906:43"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry a ſaba arri nedat me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The divine light cannot be meaſured by humane learning.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arri ſele oli ſupuit nedat mecum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Nor the divine light ſtoupe to mans capacity.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye grudging Prieſts at my name and me,</l>
               <l>I challenge ye all to diſpute in the myſtery;</l>
               <l>That is in the divine expreſſing Evangelical,</l>
               <l>The light, the depth in myſtery magical,</l>
               <l>In earth, in aire, in fire or water</l>
               <l>In Orbes in Earbs or any material matter;</l>
               <l>In Sun, in Moon, in Star or Stars, or all,</l>
               <l>The depths beneath, the ſphears Celeſtial,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Exſe me non literas homo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed devitie inſperati alvat.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hackkarim elvah halileuah ſam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arbi ſelorum madad allah al,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vita madad ai el ſonarum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alma a facti oſonet me.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Engliſh out of this myſteyous ſtate is this,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>The lighteſt light that ever ſhone,</l>
               <l>Is now letting down from Unione:</l>
               <l>Which ſhall unvail mens lights to ſee,</l>
               <l>The onely one that they in Unione be.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>My Book called <hi>Arorau Tranlagorum</hi> will ſhow my diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from all Sects printed the 25 of <hi>February</hi> 1650. It will clear many points of aſperſion laid on me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to ſerve you in love,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Theaurau-John</item>
                     <item>Tanniour <hi>the Jew.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Eval alſiel Sabbah</item>
                     <item>Skribahjail.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
